Yeah. Good morning, everyone. So, yeah,
so welcome to I Can Believe It's Not a Better,
the sixth edition. So where the
LLM needs to improve. So
yeah, we are really excited to have all of
you here. So this is a actually
six editing of this workshop. And the main
topic of this year is to, yeah,
to create a value that we can talk, like
opening a series about the
failure modes of LDR lens.
Yeah. So, yeah, it's typically, like, you know,
in machine learning, especially in the current
era of, like, foundation models,
like, people everyday are talking about
stronger, stronger, like, baseline
like, larger, models, larger
scales, emerging
behaviors or whatever yeah, that is
surprising. But many of these
most useful sex I mean,
like, scientific discovery or
scientific insights are from, like,
opposite direction.
From failures, modes, from like a pretrial
or like
negative results or careful analysis when
things doesn't really work. So
today, we're going to, focus
on exactly this kind of thing.
So where do, typically, where do LLMs
usually fall into, the shores?
Where you have hallucinate
So where do they show, like, shallow reasoning,
like, specific weakness we
face and or efficiency or other limits?
More broadly, so how can we start in
this limitations to help us
develop, like, more reliable
and more sensible systems.
Yeah. So this is also
yeah. Sorry. So this
is also like, the
aligned with the broader motivation behind
the I can't believe it's not a better initiative.
So, yeah, we are over the past,
like, few years, like almost like five years,
I guess, so the community has
grown into a huge community that's
we try to rethink how we do do
how to do research. So by
promoting transparency, promoting these
reasonable, sensible failure behaviors
over these models,
And we can help, like, align, like,
publication incentives with scientific discovery
and scientific progress. So so far,
the series has, we already have
four successful, like, new research workshops,
and one Eyecare workshop and
some other, like, a semi seminar series
with many talks dedicated to
negative results.
Yeah. So, yeah, one tip one particular,
like, encouraging sign is that this
year, New Year's, they do have a track of
collecting those negative results. I
think partially in by our
the line of workshops and the series
seminars.
Yeah. So, yeah, before we
start, we want yeah. You can also, like,
scan for our website to know about the
initiative and the community. And
also, we're committed to just drop us an email later
and to yeah. We can have more discussion.
And if if you are interested, maybe you can also
join the initiative.
Yeah. So before we start, I want to thank
everyone to join and also thank
our organizer team. So, yeah, due
to the visa issues, so some of them cannot,
join in person today.
Yeah. But, Anurag, Jennifer, and me,
we will yeah. In
this we were in the venue, like, for the whole day.
And prior, decline,
rate, and Yubin, because
of VIZHOU, they cannot join today.
And also want to thank our
adviser team, Andreas,
Tobias, Menelli, and Francisco. So
they provide
end of support and dedicated
like, advice on the whole process of
this workshop organization.
Yeah. We also want to, yeah, thank
our program committee, like,
including 81 reviewers,
who really help us make this happen.
And, yeah,
Cool. Yeah. So a few, like, quick,
housekeeping notes. So if I
going to talk today, so please make
sure your slides have sent out sent to us.
I think someone's, yeah.
And, please make sure, like, for posters,
you can hand them, like, during the coffee
break. Which should be, I think,
around, like, ten to 10:30.
And please come to us if you need any
tapes or, like, a hanging
stuff, so which should be on that table. And
also you can find me so I can help you out
to stick them. Yeah.
Yeah. And, also, please remember
to take your poster at the end of
the day before the workshop ends.
And we also have a second microphone
in the room here at yeah.
And if you need and if you need it
for questions, please raise your hand, and we will
bring it to you. Yeah. For
the remote attendees, we will take questions,
questions on the slide live just on the
IKEA website. And, yeah. If you
have any question for the remote,
remote attendees, you just type
the question into the slide slide.
So Yeah. So, yeah,
let me quickly also go over the schedule
of the date. So we were picking
we'll picking our first invite this talk
by Adam Block. And first
followed by the first set of spotlight talks and then
a coffee break. During the coffee break, you
can set up the posters. And then later
in the morning, so we would have invited talk
by Martha
and Aditi So followed by
the lunch. And in the afternoon, we will have
the poster session and
invited by and also the invited talks.
By and the c one. And
then a panel discussion on, like, where
LMs need to improve. Which will
be moderated by Jennifer.
Yeah. So we are we are very grateful
for our speakers and panelist.
For joining us today. We hope
this workshop will be
interactive, open, and
give you some, like, insights
on the failure modes of LLAM and where it
needs to be improved. Yeah.
So basically, the goal is just to
point out that world models should fail
and could fail and but you
better understand why they fail.
And what those failure modes reveal and how
we can learn from them. So
Cool. So let's get started.
So the first speaker will
be, professor Adam Block.
So from, Columbia University.
So do you want to use your
Adam, do you wanna use your own laptop or
so we can set up the
Yeah. So, yeah. So
professor Alan Block is a
system professor from computer science department
at Columbia and also a pre e ed
faculty the Department of
Electrical Engineering. So his research spans
both theoretical foundations
of machine learning with a focus on developing
algorithm that are both, like,
provably efficient and practically useful.
Yeah. And, yeah, professor,
Bloch has complete his PhD in
applied mathematics. In,
MIT, and where yeah. He
was also affiliated with the Laboratory for Information
Decision System and the Statistics
and Data Science Center. Yeah, without,
like, later, further ado. So the
floor is yours.
Thank you very much. So,
I'm Adam, and today
I'm really happy to have the chance to tell you guys about
some of the work of our group of
the last maybe year and a half or so.
Before I begin, I'd just like
to kind of give a quick shout out to especially
my junior collaborators. So this talk
is based on three papers.
The first paper, which will be about half
of the talk was led by
Audrey Huang. Who was one of
our, interns at Microsoft Research
last year. The second paper, was led
by Zheo Hao Yu, who is a master's student
at Peking And finally,
the last paper is led by Beitry Raman,
who is one of my PhD students at
Columbia. So
just to make sure that we are all kind of on
the same page, I want to motivate this
talk. By, kind of
reminding you guys of some results that,
maybe many of you already know.
So there was a very nice and fairly simple observation
out of a group at Stanford.
That they called large language monkeys.
And so the idea is that if you take
some problem, say, what is two plus
two for the sake of example, and
you feed it into a language model,
right, instead of just asking the language model to produce
a single correct completion,
you could sample many times from this model.
And maybe some of these samples are right, maybe some
of these generations are wrong, But the
point is is that as long as you have access to
some kind of oracular verifier,
right, maybe for math this is translate everything
into lean, maybe for code this is see
if something compiles. Right? But as long as you
have access to this oracular verifier,
then you can just verify each one of these generations
exhaustively and see if one of them is
correct. And obviously, What is two plus
two is a fairly simple example.
But you can imagine trying this on slightly
more complicated settings and this is precisely what
these people out of Stanford did. And they observed
that for a fairly large number of
language models, and on both
kind of math and code tasks, which are particularly
convenient, because it's kind of obvious what these verifiable
rewards should be, they found that, in fact, when you
kind of scale up the inference time compute,
in the context of this talk, we're gonna be
talking about inference time compute in terms of kind of
parallel scaling, the number of generations
per prompt, what you get is you
get kind of substantially increased performance.
The y axis here is the accuracy.
When a language model is given kind of
k, where k is on the x axis,
generations per prompt, what is the probability over
prompts that we're correct? At least one of those
generations is correct.
Now, this, paper was from two years
ago, and it was fairly influential at its time.
But the natural question, I think, is
when you run into this situation,
you might ask what if you don't actually have access
to an interact verifier?
So maybe one thing that you could do
is in some safety settings, you could have some
kind of constitutional setting where there are rule
based rewards, in which case maybe this is still irregular,
But a lot of the time people actually
just train reward models. Right?
So you usually train these reward models through
some kind of preference feedback,
and you get some kind of estimated reward,
which we'll call our hat throughout this talk,
of the quality of a given generation. And
prompt. And so in
this talk, we're going to spend a few minutes trying to understand
what happens if we try to do something similar
except we replace this oracular verifier
with this learned reward.
So let me give you a brief outline
of the rest of the talk. We're gonna
start by kind of really doing a deep dive on maybe
the most naive algorithm in
the setting, which is called best of
n. Many of you are probably familiar with it, but in
case you're not, I will kind of tell you what it is.
And we're really going to be analyzing both some of
the benefits of Best of also in
the theme of this workshop, some of the problems
with it. And,
in particular, some of those problems are going
to manifest in a lack of monochromicity.
And so in the second part of the talk,
going to discuss how we can kind of fix those
problems by kind of importing some
ideas from the theory of offline
RL, and we'll kind of get a slightly different
algorithm that will actually have improved
performance relative to best of them. And
then finally, in the last part of the talk, we're going to
take a step back and look a
little bit more deeply and interrogate of the assumptions
that went into our kind of creation of these algorithms.
And really ask, you know, to what extent are
these assumptions practical and we believe
them in real life?
So to begin, with best
event, before I kind of actually tell you what this algorithm
is, I really should tell you
kind of a formal setting in which we can think
And so for us, a language model
is always just going to be some condition
So
y. And this distribution, which
we'll call Pyref, you should think of as your language
model. After it's gone through all its
training. Right? So it's gone through all
pretraining and all forms of post training.
Right? And this is the model that you wanna see
it going to get a correct answer or not? You're gonna
be sampling from this model.
Now what's the actual goal? Well,
the goal is that we have some notion of ground
truth accuracy or ground truth reward.
Which we'll call r star.
So maybe in the context of math or code, this could
be something like a binary reward,
which is saying one if you have
a correct answer and zero otherwise. Maybe in the context
of safety, this is some kind of oracular very
good reward model that we've trained on a lot of
data. And the goal is that we'll
want to kind of output some language
model, and I use this term loosely because again, a language
model is just conditional distribution
for us, but we want to output a language
model that has high
ground truth reward.
Now we actually had access to this r star
at inference time, then we would be back
in this large language monkey setting. Right?
That would be an oracular reward. And
so we're instead going to assume only
that we have access to some kind of learned reward,
our hat, which will be kind of close to
this ground truth reward, r star, especially
on typical in And I'll
get back to kind of what this means formally in
a few slides. But
so with this reference model and this
learned reward, we have kind of a
general framework for understanding least
parallel scaling of inference time compute.
So what can your algorithms do?
Well, you can take some prompt and you
can sample some number of responses from your
reference model. And you can
score each one of those responses according
to your estimated reward. R hat. And
then using those scores, you somehow
have to return one of
those generations.
Now, which generation should you return?
The most naive thing to do is best of n.
Now best of n is a classical algorithm, you guys probably
already know what it is, but just in case you
don't, it's kind of exactly what you would
think to do. Right? If R hat is actually a good
estimate of your true reward, what you should
do is given some prompt x,
you should just sample a number of responses
from your reference model score them
according to your r hat, and just turn
the r the response that has the highest
estimated reward. And you
can ask, you know, to what extent does best event
work? And lots of people use Best Event
and have for the last large number of years.
And so of course, in many cases, it actually works
pretty well. So these curves are
kind of different language models
that are producing g s m a k responses
and this is using some fairly high quality reward
model, ArmorM. And the
y axis here is some notion of performance,
the x axis is a notion of inference time.
Compute. And if we also look at kind
of the performance on the estimated reward, which
is what best event is intending to optimize,
we see that things are going as expected.
So as we increase inference time compute, as
we scale up n, we get a concomitant
increase estimated
reward r hat. And so it
seems like best of n is working pretty well, but
we can ask to what extent this
actually a general phenomenon? And in fact,
oftentimes, Vesemind does not perform
nearly as well as this. So if we
change out the reward model, to a slightly
different reward model, we still use something
like Gemma to produce, generations
we see a much worse trend. So
first of all, our accuracy is not going
up that much. But maybe
even worse, as we scale up n,
then we're getting actually worse performance.
And this is maybe kind of in the
face of the intuition that when you talk about scaling
something, right, you're talking about scaling a
resource that you're spending. So ideally
when you're spending more of a resource, in this case, infant's
time compute, you would hope that you would then get
some, some kind of increase in the performance
itself. But that's not what's happening
here. Right? We're seeing actually quite a lot of decrease
over here. Moreover, if we
kind of look at what happens with the estimated
reward r hat instead of r star, we see
that we are just kind of increasing r
hat. So as you scale up inference time compute,
best event is doing what we expect it
to be doing. And so it's natural to ask
really what is going on and how we can fix it.
And to some extent, the answer to what
is going on here is really,
in what sense is r hat a good
estimate of r star?
So I said that r hat is kind of an approximation
of r star, but what does this actually mean?
And maybe to motivate the kind of following
definition of closeness, we should ask how is
r hat actually trained? Right? Usually,
the way that you train, like, an estimated
reward function is that you either use preference
feedback or you sue use some kind of other
data and you just try and kind of maybe
solve within the Bradley Terry model.
Right? But it actually matters
what kind of data you use to train your
reward model. And typically, you're going to be
using, well, typical generation
y, maybe from something like your reference model.
And so it's maybe reasonable to assume
that for typical generations,
sampled from your kind of reference model, you should
expect that r hat has a good predictor of
r star. So you could actually
formalize this by saying, that
in expectation, over typical generations,
you expect that the squared error between our
hat, your estimated reward, and
r star, your true reward, is
relatively small. Smaller than some epsilon.
So Now, epsilon is not going
to be zero. Right? If epsilon is zero,
we're back to the setting of a regular reward.
But we can imagine that epsilon is actually quite small.
We've done a good job of training our reward.
And so we can then ask, you know, what is going
wrong? And what's going wrong is
something called reward hacking, or the
term that has kind of comes from economics,
is Goodhart's Law. So when a metric
becomes a target, it ceases to be a useful
metric. In this case, our metric
is this estimated reward our
hat. And the target, of
course, is that by doing
So And
so as we start optimizing toward this
r hat, it ceases to be
a very good estimator of the true reward, r
star. Now what does
this mean in kind of theory?
Well, we're assuming, right, that on typical generations,
the squared error is small.
But best of n does not return typical
generations. Right? What it does
is that it returns generations that are selected
for having a very high estimated
reward r hat. And so on the actual
policy or language model that we return,
it could be the case that our squared error,
the quality of r hat as an estimator of
r star, is actually very bad.
Right? And this is kind of
precisely what's going on. We this non monophonic
plot that we were seeing. Now
we can actually say a little bit more and a little bit
more rigorously about this. But in order
to do that, we have to kind of have a better sense of kind
of what controls, what factors go in
to the performance of best event.
And intuitively, there are really kind of two factors
that should govern this performance.
The first is the quality of our reference model.
So the better that our language model is,
the better best of n should do. And this should
be true both kind of statistically in the sense that
for kind of some fixed n, we get a better
performance, but it should also be true computationally
in the sense that if we have some target level
of performance, then we should not need as many
generations, in order to reach that.
Target level. Now the second
thing that should go into the the
quality of best of n is, the quality of the reward
model. So intuitively, if the
reward model is worse, then best event
should perform worse. Right? And
we've actually already kind of just discussed this
by kind of saying that the quality of the reward
model is just governed by this expected squared error.
So So how should we actually
control in some kind of rigorous
sense the quality of the reference
model itself? And
one way to do this is through a notion that
we call coverage. So there are different
kind of slightly different notions coverage that
have been proposed in a number of different papers.
This notion of coverage is the
follows on the screen. So remember, you
should think of PyTorch as some language model
that is able to return kind of your
correct answers with very high probability.
And Pyref is our kind of fixed model.
What coverage is saying is that if coverage
is small, then pi ref is very
close to pi star. Meaning that we're
doing a good job of covering correct answers.
Whereas if Pyraph is very far from Pystar,
we should expect coverage to be quite
large. There are a few alternative
notions of coverage that you could consider.
We do consider it in a few different
papers, including one that was here in our
for the theorists in the audience, maybe I can just mention
that this notion of coverage should be a little
bit familiar and that it's just equal to a monotone
transform of the Chi square
divergence. Not familiar with the chi square divergence,
don't worry. It's just a stronger form of the
KL divergence. And it won't really be relevant. For the
rest of the talk. Talk.
So, you know, we introduced this definition
but we could ask, you know, empirically, is coverage
actually small? And this
large language monkey's paper is actually essentially
saying that yes. So for a lot of reasonable
tasks and a lot of reasonable language models,
coverage is relatively small.
So And so how can we use
these two notions to kind of
n? Well,
we have the following theorem,
which says that as
long as kind of our n is sufficiently large,
then the kind of sub optimality of best
of n, so the expected kind of
ground truth reward r star according to our
best event policy, with respect to some
comparator policy pi star.
Is controlled by two terms.
So the first term this c
cove over n, is really a measure again
of the quality of the reference model.
And the second term square root of
n epsilon squared, is a measure of the quality
of the reward.
Moreover, this bound is actually
tight. So best event will perform like
this. There are kind of reward models such that
you cannot improve on this.
Now, this bound actually does a pretty good job
of describing the empirical behavior
that we were observing.
So remember, in this kind of non monotone,
transition, we really had
two phases. Right? We had kind of an increasing
phase and a decreasing phase.
The increasing phase occurs kind of a
small n regime. So in the
small n regime, if we think of n
epsilon sorry. If we think of epsilon square
as relatively small, then n epsilon square for
small n will also be small.
And so here, what really dominates is this
coverage over n. And so as you increase
n, coverage over n is getting smaller, which
means that regret is getting smaller. Which
means that our performance is actually getting better.
Right? So that's why we see improved performance.
So On the other hand, for the large
n regime, right,
this first term really doesn't matter. For
n big, this is very small, and what really
matters is the second term. And now
as we increase n, we're increasing n times
epsilon squared, which means our regret is getting
bigger. And this leads to
decreased performance, which is exactly what's going on
here.
So a few more remarks
about this, result.
So first is that with kind of optimally
tuned n, right, we can never actually do this in
practice. We don't know what coverage is. We don't know
what epsilon squared is. But we might ask, what is the
ceiling of performance for best of ben?
And the serum actually gives you some scaling.
So it's the coverage coefficient to the one
third times epsilon to the two third.
Now, kind of bound doesn't
really mean anything in the abstract, but we'll
compare it to an alternative method. In
the next section of the talk.
So really, the question here is
we've done a pretty good job of analyzing best of
n. Right? We kind of understand how this works.
We understand how this translates into practice. But
it's natural to ask if we can actually do better.
Are there any kind of strategies that we can use to,
first of all, improve the ceiling of performance
and second of all, remove this
annoying lack of monochromicity.
And it turns out that the answer is yes.
So we can instantiate something called pessimism,
talk a little bit more about the etymology of pessimism
in the third part of the talk. But we can
instantiate pessimism, and this
will kind of completely mitigate this reward hacking.
Phenomenon. So
what is really going on for the ceiling of performance?
Why are we not getting some very good ceiling of
performance? Well, in some sense, we're asking this
parameter n to do double duty.
Right? First, it kind of appears
in this first term, and second, it appears
in this second term. Right?
And order to kind of better
understand how we can improve on best of n, we
we can ask, you know, what is best of
n really doing? So it's trying
to optimize this r hat, this estimated
reward, but it's subject to some kind of regularization.
So one other way to write
this best event policy is as a solution to
this variational problem. So
it's essentially the policy that maximizes
the expected estimated reward.
Minus some regularization term that depends
on n. Right?
Now, we're also using exactly
n samples to sample from this policy.
So the problem here is that n is being used twice
and we can't really tune it in the correct
way. Right? Because kind of
tuning interferes. Either if n is too small,
right, then maybe we can't sample from a good
policy. If that is too large, then we don't have enough
regularization.
So So maybe what we should do is that we should
kind of replace this regularization being
function of n with kind of a different form of regularization.
And maybe to help motivate what that should
be, we should ask, you know, what do we actually want
out of a policy? So the only
thing we really know is that r hat is a good
estimator of r star, on pyref.
Right? We know that in squared error on typical
samples, we have a good estimate.
And so really what we want to do is we want
to ensure that the policy that we return, the language
model that we return is actually somewhat similar to
Pyref. Right? So we really want
a sample from some Py beta. So
beta will be some tuning parameter and,
you know, we'll maximize the
expected, estimated reward minus
some regularization term.
So this leaves us with two questions. So
the first question is, what is the regularization?
And the second one is how should we actually sample
from this policy?
So let's get to the first one. Well,
remember, all of this is really about solving,
Goodhart's Law. When a metric becomes a
target, it ceases to be a useful metric.
The way that we can kind of quantitatively solve this problem
is just to note that a special
property of coverage is that
if we look at the squared error on some policy
pie, then we can actually control it
by the coverage coefficient
times the squared error on this policy Piref.
And we know that the squared error on the policy
pyref is small. Right? So
as long as coverage is not too large,
then Goodhart's law is not really a problem. We
cannot reward hack.
And so this naturally suggests that we should
use coverage as a regular regularizer.
Now this leads maybe to the next question,
which is you know, this is all very
well to write down some variational problem.
But how should we actually sample from this?
Right? You know, you want some algorithm
that kind of given your reference model and given
your reward function, can actually produce some return.
And it's really not obvious what how to do
that from kind of this expression.
And the answer is something called approximate rejection
sampling. So rejection sampling originated back in the
nineteen fifties with Von Neumann, with
Yuri Polanski, we had a paper from
a few years ago on kind of how to generalize this.
Beyond bounded density ratios.
But really the key point is that you can actually just directly
solve this variation problem. I'm not going to
write what the closed form solution actually is, but you
do get a very simple closed form. You
can just plug this into rejection sampling.
You're not familiar with rejection
sampling, there's a way in which you can take some
target distribution and you have a proposal
distribution that you can easily sample from. In our case,
pyref. And your target distribution
will be this pi beta. And as long as you know
the density ratio, can kind of efficiently
sample from this target distribution.
So again, I mean, I'm happy to answer
offline precisely what this form is. It's not
very hard, but maybe just for the sake of simplicity,
we you can believe me that in fact it is
quite simple. And if you
kind of look at the performance of the
resulting policy, it has a slightly different form from
that of best event.
So now we're looking again at the, the
suboptimality. Terms of expected true
reward r star with respect to our competitor
policy pi hat. And now this performance
is controlled by the square root of coverage
times epsilon squared, plus some function
of coverage and some function of epsilon
squared. And maybe
the key thing to note here is that the
performance is never degrading with n.
Right? Because we've kind of removed n. From
the kind of expression. So
it actually takes about coverage over beta,
number of samples in order to actually sample
from this policy, and we'll actually see this empirically
in the next slide.
So The next point to observe is, again,
we can ask for what is the ceiling of performance?
Here. Right? What if we optimally tune beta? You
know, we can't actually do that. We don't know what coverage
is. But suppose we want to know what the ceiling
of performance is, and we see that this is square root
of coverage. Times epsilon squared.
And note that this is actually significantly better
than that of best of n.
Moreover, this performance is actually
optimal in two ways. So first of all, it's statistically
optimal, meaning that matter how many kind of
samples you take, if you only are assuming
that you're reward your
reward estimate, our hat is kind of close
in squared error on typical samples,
you cannot get a better suboptimality than
this. But it's also computationally optimal,
meaning that if you want to target this degree of
suboptimality, this inference time
pessimism algorithm, which is just sampling from pi
hat beta, is kind of optimal.
It uses a minimal number of samples to do that.
So that's a lot of theory. We can ask, does
this actually work? And in fact,
it does work pretty well. So
the dark lines here are the infant's
time pessimism, The dash lines are
best of n, And, again,
the x axis is the number of responses
per prompt. We can see that, you know,
we don't necessarily see that much of a higher
ceiling with respect to, instant time pessimism
as opposed to best of n. But we do
see that it is kind of successfully
combating reward So We'll
get back in the third part why we might not see a higher
ceiling. Now
we can also see why this is occurring. So if
we look at the estimated reward, best
event is kind of doing what we tell it to. It is increasing this
estimated reward, which is leading to
the reward hacking behavior, whereas inference time pessimism
is not. Once it gets to a certain end, it's saturating,
which again is kind of what we expect out of the analysis.
So Okay. So this was maybe
one way of solving this issue with best
of then. But now we should really take a step back
and try and kind of figure out what are the issues
this. Right? For one, we did not see that much
of a lift in the kind of ceiling of performance.
So Now we're going to take a step back by
kind of examining, two
different, facets. One
is we're going to be looking at the difference between
policy and reward
level pessimism. And
two, is we're gonna ask, you know, is
the metric that we're actually targeting here, which
is expected ground truth reward
r star, is this actually a reasonable
metric?
Okay. So So let's start
with the policy and reward level pessimism.
And we can ask, you know, what have we done so far? Well,
we've analyzed best event,
Right? And we've also kind of solved some of the
issue. We've also validated this empirically.
Right? And in theory, this is very
nice. This is actually a fairly clean solution
to the problems that we were observing. But
it's natural to wonder, what are the assumptions
that are actually going into this theory and how realistic
are they?
So for example, how reasonable is it
the assumption that we have small expected squared
error? Right? I'll
go into this a little bit more in a
few slides, but but maybe before we do
we can ask you know, why is this even called infincent
time pessimism and the answer
is really from RL. So a lot of my background
is in RL, if you're not familiar with
kind of some of the terminology in RL,
maybe a very simple, kind of breakdown
is that in online RL, where we have
interactive feedback, we want to do
optimism. And optimism is reward over
estimation. Why do you want to do optimism? It's
because it encourages exploration.
So if you have some uncertainty and you kind of
add this uncertainty to your reward and you're overestimating
your reward in uncertain regions,
then your algorithm will go to those uncertain
regions. And that's really
good because you get this online feedback.
But the kind of setting of inference
time alignment where we don't really have
any actual feedback when we're running
these, best of end type algorithms except
for this estimated reward model.
Is really closer to an offline setting, where
we just have a fixed batch of data we
have to decide how we use it. And here
we want to do pessimism. Which is reward
underestimation. And this is because exploration
in kind of an offline setting is actually very
bad. Because we don't know anything about
the distribution outside of what we've seen. We don't get
more feedback. And so we want to penalize
any form of exploration.
Now, what is, kind of pessimism
in kind of math? It's really
just saying that our reward estimates
are actually smaller than the true
reward. R star. And if this
is the case, then we can't really reward hack. Because
optimizing r hat is certainly making r star go up
at least to a extent.
Now, instantiated this through something
that you might think of as policy level pass
pessimism. Right? We solved some regularized variational
problem to ensure that, kind of
expected rewards are not too high. But
this is actually maybe a less natural way of
doing pessimism if your background is in RL.
Really, you might think, we should be doing
reward level pessimism. Now,
how do you actually do reward level pessimism?
Well, if the rewards are pessimistic, right, we cannot
reward hack. And the kind of classical
way to kind of instantiate pessimistic
rewards is you introduce uncertainty estimates.
So we'll say u of x y this
will be some measure of how much do
we know about this generation y.
And we'll then force our pessimism by just
subtracting uncertainty from the estimated
reward. R hat. So the idea
here is that if our uncertainty is small,
when r hat is actually a good estimator, which happens
on kind of typical generations
and it's large otherwise, then this will
indeed be a pessimistic reward estimate.
So then the natural question is, how do you actually get
this uncertainty estimate? And
we kind of borrow some ideas from
a more classical
where from about almost ten years
ago now, to kind of construct
this uncertainty quant. Now
there's a lot of empirical details that
go into this, but but
if you believe this, then you should maybe
believe that this, using best event with these
kind of pessimistic reward estimates will actually
perform better. And in fact, that is the case.
So the green is our kind of pessimistically constructed
reward and the other colors
kind of different notions of reward.
And here we actually do see an improvement
on the ceiling, which again is somewhat
So now I really only have a few minutes
before I should take questions.
So let me just kind of really
briefly kind of go through what some of
maybe the other issues with the theory. Are.
Right? So observed that we had
kind of some reasonable performance on this GSMA
k benchmark. Maybe we didn't have a huge
increase in the ceiling of reward.
But this is a nice instance. On some
other kind of tasks, we do not really see much
of a signal. So this is Alpaca eval.
If you're not familiar with this, this
is instead of, like, actually getting an accuracy,
what you do is that you have some question and your
language model answers the question and you kind
of compare it in terms of pairwise feedback to
some ground truth set of, like, good answers.
And in this kind of model, maybe
optimizing your expected reward
is not the right thing. To do.
Moreover, coverage might not be kind of
the correct most natural
assumption, and finally, squared error might not.
Be good. So we're going
to ignore this notion of coverage, I said,
there are some other notions, but this is a little bit more
technical. Feel free to ask me after the talk if you're
curious. But let's maybe focus a little
bit more on whether expected is
a good model. So in fact,
it oftentimes is not because it may not
be meaningful right, beyond binary
signals. For something like pairwise error,
never actually see this r star. So it doesn't really
mean anything. To make our, like, our hat
very large.
Second, alpac eval is measuring win
rate instead of expected reward. Right?
So again, like making our star very, very
large, is, you know, not that
reasonable. And so maybe a more
natural goal is you want to kind of optimize
win rate. Right? So you want to optimize
the probability that your model beats some reference
model.
Second, you know, is squared error assumption
very reasonable? And lot
of the times, it's not. Right? So one reason that
it's maybe very easy to see that this is not so
reasonable that it's not monotone and
variant. If you scale our hash by some
constant factor, then it doesn't change the performance of
best of n, but it very much does change
the performance of this kind of squared
error. And second of all, once again,
r star is not really a real quantity in
a lot of cases. It doesn't really mean anything
to say that our r hat is close to r star.
If all we get is preference feedback, then probably
what we should care about is kind of winning
in preference feedback.
So So the solution is that maybe we should assume
some kind of probability of ranking error. If you
take two samples from your reference
model, what is the probability that your
learned reward model, r hat, ranks
them incorrectly. And
just at a kind of very high level,
what you can show is that actually now the ceiling
of best event under this assumption once
again becomes And you
can instantiate pessimism in such a
way to ensure monotonousity.
So all of this kind of theory and analysis
goes through it empirically actually works pretty
well. So let me just
briefly summarize the talk and kind of conclude
with smoking questions, and then I'm happy to take any questions.
So first, the difficulty of infant time
scaling is really governed by the parameter
coverage. Best of end can do well, but
it really depends on the quality of the reward
model, but it will not scale monotonically,
unfortunately. Due to this reward hacking
phenomenon, and pessimism can
really actually mitigate this in a number of different
forms. So which algorithm you should
actually run really kind of does depend on the target
metric. And you know,
actually that kind of final statement is really maybe
the first one of these open questions. Is is
there a more general paradigm to kind of have a better
understanding of which algorithms you should run for
inference time alignment.
Second is know, I gave
you kind of one empirical way to enforce
reward level pessimism, but but
we certainly don't know in general what are the
best ways. And finally,
all of this talk was on parallel
scaling. But what we oftentimes care a lot more
about are serial scaling paradigm.
Right? Very long chains of thought. And
it's natural to wonder if you can kind of apply
some similar ideas and some similar techniques
to kind of ensure a lack of reward hacking.
When we are subject to inference time scaling.
So thanks a lot, and I'm happy to take any questions.
So any question from the audience?
Yep. Sure.
Yeah. Thanks for the great talk. I
was just wondering when you during your presentation,
how do you how do you
compute the the coverage in practice?
Or, like, what does it look like you know,
in the code? Yeah. Yeah.
So that's a great question.
So there are maybe a few answers to this. One
answer in the kind of specific context
of this talk, you actually don't
ever need to compute the coverage.
The algorithm that you run is kind of agnostic
to that. The kind of optimal tuning
parameters do depend on that. We still
recommend some degree of parameter tuning,
for that. Maybe
a broader answer is that there we have a paper
called the Coverage Principle
answer
some of those questions a little bit more.
Other questions from the audience?
Yeah. Sure.
Thanks for the talk.
My question is that you have a class
of problems like you said in the beginning
that you have a right question,
you know that two plus two is four.
And you also have a class of problems,
a class of prompts that should
don't actually know what is the correct
answer. So is it possible to
train a network
for, at the same time,
achieving the correct answers that
you know what r star is.
And also
doing this reward level pessimism
for when you don't know?
Yeah. So I guess
as soon as you mix in the uncertainty, right, you're
going to be somewhat subject to reward hacking.
Unless you're kind of careful with the design of
your reward model. If
you can already identify those problems for
which you do have, like, an oracular verify
reward, then that
you should just essentially run best event with
that oracular verifiable reward.
If you can't do that identification, then that's
kind of already contained in this notion of the
estimated reward. And you
should do, like, a estimation.
Great. Yeah. Thank you thank you,
Adam, again for the great talk. And
yeah,
thanks.
Yeah. So we will shortly start our
Spotlight talks.
Let me set up the talk.
So the authors of
the first three spotlight talks if you're
here already, then peace. Yeah.
Be more to the front so you can go
easily on the stage when you're presenting.
Okay. We will probably wait
for one minute for the first talk
if Yeah. So,
otherwise, we can start the second talk
first. Like, it's
keep waiting for one minute. Sorry for the delay.
Yeah, if your paper was lost in translation,
why SOTA l m struggle with French
NLU frontiers? Now is your last chance? To give
you a spotlight talk?
No. But you do the sharpness aware one afterwards.
Right? Right.
Yeah. So I think we should go ahead with the
second spotlight talk already.
So hello, everyone. Thanks
for coming. I'm Prashant Waltz, and
yeah, I'm here today to discuss
about an interesting phenomena
that we have been observing for the past one year
where a better pretrained model doesn't
always lead to a better downstream model.
And we show ways how we can mitigate this.
So first off, I want to ask a question.
So how do model builders decide
their optimization decisions?
So, generally, pretraining choices
are tuned to optimize the base model.
For example, learning rates or
the optimizer opt or the
optimizer are decided to minimize
the pretraining loss. However,
models are trained using a multistage pipeline.
You have pre training, followed by
post training, which includes fine tuning,
reinforcement learning, or even quantization.
So, essentially, our goal is to get
a base model that is good
after all these modifications.
We argue that the pretraining loss
alone doesn't capture the base model's
ability to adapt So instead, we
study this learning for getting trade off.
So more precisely,
we take a base model, which is pre trained on a large data, and
then fine tune it on a dataset.
On the x act we vary the hyperparameters
and train various checkpoints.
And on the x axis, we plot
the, loss on the original pretraining
task. And on the y axis, we plot
the loss on the fine tuning task.
So we can see that the
model with the best fine tuning performance actually
has some degradation on the
pretraining task. Our goal to
get similar or even better fine tuning
performance and try to reduce
this degradation. This is also
called as catastrophic forgetting.
In our work, we show that reducing the sharpness
of the pretraining loss can actually improve
this learning for getting trade off.
And yeah, we evaluate
three changes to the optimizer to minimize
the sharp First
off, it's, via explicit minimization.
We use sharpness aware minimization or
the SAM optimizer. SAM essentially
minimizes the sensitivity to
nearby perturbations. So
like, fine tuning can be thought of as a perturbation
where we shift the base model parameters
Hence, we try Sam. And implicitly,
we look at learning rates where
we control the peak learning rates and also
the time spent decaying the learning
rate. And these are our
main results from ALM two one b.
We take a pretrained checkpoint and then only
mid train it using Adam which
we call the ALMU baseline and also
using SAM. The
horizontal line in this plot is the base
model performance on the pretraining task
and then we fine tune it on MetaMask
or Tulu. And we see that there's
some drop in the pre training performance on
the pre training task. And we can
see that Sam has lesser forgetting. Even
though it had a slightly worse
performance to begin with.
We also see similar results for quantization,
where we quantize the model to four bits
and we see Sam again has 40% less degradation.
Apart from these results, we also perform a
control study where we do
experiments at a smaller scale and
pre train a model from scratch and then fine
tune. And, again,
we can see that Sam achieved a superior learning
for getting trade off, and
in our paper, we also show that Sam's performance
scales with increasing the number of pretraining
tokens and also the size of the model.
Yeah. Now to also check the role of implicit
minimization, we again pre train
a model from scratch using Adam But
this time, we just vary the pretraining learning
rate. And if you look at
this plot, you can see that the learning rate of three minus
four actually gets the lowest
pretraining loss. So, ideally,
a model builder would choose this learning
rate as the for the pretraining
model and then fine tune it.
However, we see that it's actually the
learning rate with the higher loss that gets the
better learning for getting trade off.
Which is surprising.
And so to
conclude, I want to emphasize that
optimization decisions, which seems
suboptimal initially actually lead to a better
final model. And we urge
the model builders to also look at other factors
such as sharpness of the model, when
making their optimization decisions.
If you're more interested in knowing about our work,
like the intuition behind why we minimize
sharpness, or an empirical
analysis of sharpness minimization.
Please come and, visit our poster.
Thank you.
Thanks, Feng, for a great talk. So
yeah, then we will move
forward in Yahoo.
Yeah. I'm just gonna start. You
can use the
So, hello everyone.
My name is Yakub Binkovs,
and today I want to present you
our recent work, which is titled
Attention Sinks, as Internal Signals
for Hallucination Detection in Large Language Models.
And this is work, we
did with Camille Adams and
Tomas Khaydanovich.
So, I think that we all
agree on the fact that LLMs
produce hallucinations and the is
a really big issue, especially when it comes
to deployment
or, other real world, applications.
And, we
recently saw some, of
works which were focused on
providing hallucination detectors based
on attention
attention weights or attention mechanism
analysis. And
personally, I, recognize this
area as a really promising,
research direction because
think it not only provide us with
great detectors and methods
for spotting hallucinations,
but on also give us,
some insight into the
operation and mechanism of the large language
models. And,
we dig deeper into this
direction and,
started wondering whether
this several previous
works has some
common common unifying
principle and found that
attention sync scores can be
implicitly, used by several
previous detectors.
And, by using attention
syncs, scores in our work, we show that
we can get really strong
signal for hallucination detection.
But to make us, to make
all of us are on the same page,
I'd like to start
attention syncs because
these are just meaningless, most
of the time, meaningless, tokens
which absorb most of the attention
during inference. And
they they have a function
to, abstain from attending
to some semantic tokens when,
it's shouldn't be any attention
to them. And sync
scores can, give us the a measure
of syncness of a
specific token, and we,
leverage that to
perform hallucination detection in our
method. Called SyncProbe.
So, during inference, we gather,
all attention maps from LLM,
and, select compute sync scores
for each token, for each liar and hat,
and then sort them select top,
k values of sync scores
and concatenated fit fit.
This into hallucination detection probe
which in our case is logistic regression model.
And before I,
dig deeper into the
results of our empirical studies, I would like
to show you some,
our analysis, why
this sync probe exactly works.
So just to recap, you see here,
regular multi
head attention equation and
turns out that, for attention sync,
you can, observe very small value
vector norms, and,
this is obviously, much
motivated by the fact that when you don't want
to fetch any meaningful
information, you don't need to
large magnitude of of these value vectors.
And, and when
analyzing our model and in trying
to interpret what it has learned,
observed that, whenever the model
the hallucination probe, sees
some feature as important,
we can spot, larger,
value vector norms. In
the inference of LLM.
And, maybe there is no doubt
theoretical claim, but
it is really nice observation
and I think worth studying
even more. But going back to
the empirical result,
we observed outperformance
on, the previous method in most
of the configurations.
And compared to six attention based
baselines. And this high
performance was observed,
on the models from 3,000,000,000 up
to 12,000,000,000 of parameters
from different, architectures,
and model families. So, here you can
see the excerpt from the
results, and I encourage you to visit the
paper to see the full
results table. So, to conclude,
we in our work, not only,
provided, a
new hallucination detection method,
But I think that also
pointed to the really important
direction for the future research and to
study more on information flow in
LLMs. And, looking forward
to perform more studies
on this topic. And
thank you for your attention, and I encourage
you to visit our poster
on the today's poster session. Thank you.
Thanks again. And,
yeah. So, we will have a
debrief from ten to
10:30. And after that, we will have a
talk, from Mater.
Yeah. So for the
presenters, you can set up the
all the posters during this TBR.
And please, feel free to reach out to
me if you need some help on setting
up the poster.
Directly predicting the prediction so giving
predictions. And my question is,
how would that approach basically
extend to other tabular data? So
is is that where we should
be going? And if we if we
do that, so for example, we could prompt
Hello? Oh, yeah. We could prompt
or or instruct the LMM
A statistical model. Right?
Use and you can use any of these random
forest search and search. So if we
do that, then would
that approach essentially solve all these
and what are the challenges that would still remain open?
Thanks. So you can do that and
there are papers that actually do that, like this
paper. And that's totally fair.
But what we are advocating out
for is that the model itself that does the
prediction should be a foundation model. So meaning, we
just need an architecture that adapts,
and there are a few up there. There's Tabicle,
there's Tapia Fence. So there's some initial
foundation models for Tabio Research. That
themselves, like an LLM, take in rows and columns
and do predictions directly. Right?
And because it's a foundation model, the amount
of training data and resources you would need, you
can't just generate it on the fly and say, can
you predict the code? Implements a foundation
model? Trains it for 2,000,000 steps, and then
does the prediction. Right? So I think there definitely needs
to be some pre training like in the
foundation realm. Then of course, you can always like
ask an agent to say, can you
adapt something that works within this
foundation model? But we do believe
that the strength is gonna come from actually implementing
a different type of architecture, the equivalent
of LLMs basically but for
for for tabular, which will be FTNs.
Thank you. I wanted to
ask what's your take, between, like, the
relation between tabular foundation and
graph foundation models. Because
there are a bunch of people who are working
in representing tables as, like, Aruccino's
graphs. And so graph foundation
model seems like a promising
approach to deal with that. So do you see some
connections between the two? And what's your take on
on this topic Yeah. For sure.
I think as as always, I think a
lot of topics can be casted onto
graphs. I think we have the same thing with, like, transformers
and graph neural network and so on. So I definitely
think that you can cast a tabular problem
as a graph problem, especially what people are
doing now when you have multi table. I think that is
where the graph really shines. I do
think that there will be some graph
in foundation tabular models, whether we
whether people want it or not, it needs to.
There is some
tabular specific properties, which you
could encode in the graph sense as
well. But that arguably don't need it to be
just a graph. Per se. So
yeah. As before, I think it could be
it can be casted onto a graph. There will be some graph.
For now, they're going sometimes a bit together,
but there are also stabs that don't necessarily cast
it onto a graph. Per se. Sometimes graphs
yeah, might be restricting in the way that you don't
want the the the prior or the structure
to be restricted. Unclear. I think we're very early
days. Thank you.
Move all the way to the back.
You're giving fun a good workout.
Hi. Sorry.
So really do you think
this is an architectural problem or a
data structure? And I
ask this because there are some
other use cases where you know,
modeling template from each model as kind of a
sequence you know, just
modeling as a sequence, like,
you know, genetic foundation models.
Do you think it makes sense to model this
with a transformer or any very
Or do you think it this is ultimately
a architecture problem
transformers do not generalize well to tetra
features. Or anything like that. Mhmm.
It's both, I would say.
I think because of arguments like
from a memory point of view, you can't fit the whole
table into a transformer, I don't think you can just
use attention as it is full, all
to all attention across the table. It's just not gonna
work. The way people for example are
currently going at it with the initial wave of,
tabular foundation models is that they first
attend row wise, then they attend
column wise, this is an attempt that kinda
taking into account the structure of a table,
while being computationally tractable. Right? So
I think there's definitely an element of we can't
just use a monolithic transformer. That's not
gonna work. However, you point make a great point. It's
also data. Right? It's only so far seen
this one dimensional prediction. Right? And we are gonna
have to start training on tabular data. Which
is quite hard because they're not as
easy to find as just text on the
Internet. It needs to be a table. It needs
to have a predictive task that you want to do. Right?
And so on. So both of these are quite,
quite important. Depending to answer
your last question, depending on the task
if the task is just again, just
a single sequence that you're trying to then predict the
the structure, for example.
I think a normal trans LLM might be able
to do it just because, again, it resembles the
normal setup quite, easily. However, if
you say, look, I'm predicting the sequence but I have this whole
table of other properties and chemical
properties and whatnot that I want to use as well, I would say
you're moving more into the tabular realm. Right? So I think
it'll depend how on how much it resembles
the language prediction task versus the
big tabular problem. If that makes sense. Yeah. That
makes a lot of sense. Sorry to follow-up
on this as well. Please. What is
so on the same idea
of fitting the data distribution,
based on the fact that you're proposing a
different architecture for this type of data,
What do you think is the role of
reasoning on top of this, your data
distribution? Do you think it fits?
Training with both language
and other types of data And
you think it requires reasoning for how?
Have a better prediction of you know,
tabular data? Yep. I think
I I think reasoning will always help. I think reasoning
will also help it a So
to specific tasks. Right? For me, the
big architecture in the pretraining
leverages this whole in context learning
that you can't get from just like,
from just quickly training something on the fly.
So you do need to do a lot of pre training. This is very
powerful. It creates a general
algorithm. Now this general algorithm is gonna do much
better on a specific task if you then allow
an agent to iterate over it and say, look, you have this pretrained
model. It's good at most things. It's not the
best at anything. Can you now fit it
to the task? Right? So for me, it's always these
two, but one needs the other. Cannot just have an agent
iterate on this alone because it doesn't work. Right?
You need a bit of both.
Hi. Hey. Thank you so much for such
an amazing talk. Yeah. So my
question is about whether we can
tabular data as a new modality similarly to
how we represent images as a
new modality, and then we just plug
them into the our
foundation language models. Mhmm.
So the main argument that I would see against it
initially is, again, that it's too
large to just make ahead and just plug
it into an existing language model.
It would have to be preprocessed
with something else. This is not to say
that you cannot leverage part of the algorithm
with a huge already pre trained foundation model, that
might work very well. But there needs to be
some research in how do we get
this into a state that actually
LLM can use. Right? Which is not quite clear
yet. And this becomes even more complex when we talk about
many tables and, like, millions of rows and
so on. How do we make this palatable? Right?
And there's two options. Either we start from scratch or
we say, let's make an adapter and
I'm not aware of anyone having gone
down that route yet. But there might
be.
Yeah. Cool. So due to the time limit, we can
still take only still
take one more question? Okay. Cool.
Thanks, Wilbur. Thanks for the
great talk.
With tabular data, there's so many different
ways of posing the problem and, like Yes. You know,
myriads of different
solutions to, like, machine learning on tabular data.
I'm curious with your approach you've talked about,
kind of like
this conjunction between, like, an agentic workflow
and sort of foundational model, I'm
curious how you're thinking about the
problem framing and how to separate those
two tasks. Like,
specifically around, like, the foundational model part,
and what do you think that will, like,
solve better than
existing workflows?
As in how do you define the
let me start answering, and then we'll see if that can
somewhere. All of this assumes and
and you're very right there that the
task needs to be defined mathematically. So you can't just
say for example, look at my table and tell me things
which some clients by the way like, would like
to, but that doesn't work. Right? We have we are it's
very well defined in like here's some examples,
predict for the same this. This is for now how we're
treating that's the meta learning setup and that's what we're
currently doing. Now you could have
an agent in theory look
at a a table and
say, okay, you say you wanna produce
revenue. These these these
look like this could be the one that you want to
predict. I still think at the end of the day, it has to go
back to a human who says, yes, this is what I want to predict,
this mathematically defines the objective,
Now go and do it. Right? The the underlying
foundation model itself
will need a clear objective. That's for sure.
What do you then build on top? Agentically, I think
that's a bit maybe more on the product side and maybe
a bit more flexible. Does that answer your
question? Sort of. I
I think I was trying to drill a little more into, like,
the the, problem
formulation of the foundational model. Uh-huh.
You know, what what, how you're
generalizing this at that level.
But it's okay. I can
follow-up. Let's start offline. Yeah. Yeah. Great.
Great. Let's
Yeah. So we
will still have go to the post
spotlight session But due to
some travel constraints, so two of our
think two of the papers the authors from two of
the papers cannot join in person. So
we will just play their
record. But due to the, yeah,
due to the time constraint, maybe we could
could just play one of them. And afterwards,
we will give a spotlight talk in person.
Later for the third talk.
Hi, everyone.
I'm Fer Hassan, and today I'm presenting
our paper. I can I can't believe it's not safer,
preference safety? This was in clinical
LLM. Evaluation.
The main claim is a, a
model definition, prefer overall,
It's not necessarily the safest clinical
model. This matter because
many LLM evaluation pipelines rely
on preference signals we ask users or experts
which answer is better. Aggregate
the votes, and build a leaderboard.
But in medicine, better overall can hide
safety critical issues. In Move,
which stands for Massive Open
Online Validation Evaluation Platform,
it allows us to test this directly because
it captures two signals, side
by side blind blinded
pairwise preference. And detailed
clinical rubric ratings. So the paper is not only evaluating
models, it's evaluating
the the evaluation signal itself.
So white preference can be
about safety proxy. The problem is
that preference and safety are not the same kind
of signal. Pairwise
preference which answer is
better overall,
that gives us scalable ranking signal.
But clinical, clinical safety requires
something more specific. We need
to know whether the answer is harmful, whether
it is accurate, whether it omits
important flags, and whether it manages.
Uncertainty appropriately. A response
can be persuasive, fluent,
detailed, or longer. And therefore win
the preference vote while still containing
a clinically meaningful mistake.
So the core question, we ask
is when clinicians prefer one answer,
that that preference actually track safety,
critical, quality? So
to tell you more about, like, the move dataset
and what's the snapshot, what we kept, captured,
The strengths of this study comes from this
move dataset. In this
snapshot snapshot, analyze the feedback
from 776 clinicians
in over 28 countries. And
we we see the output from certain clinical
LLMs. Across 76
specialties. The platform
captures two complementary form of evaluation.
First, clinicians provide
multi criteria rubric
on a scale from minus two to two, minus two
being worse and plus two being very
good, the negative score minus one or
minus two count as
clinically meaningful failures
Second clinicians provide
the 18,685
blinded per watt shipment preference,
which is basically between the two answer,
which answer is is preferred
for the specific clinical case.
Because both signals are collected in the same platform,
we can directly audit whether
the preference leaderboard aligns with the safety
critical criteria like
the harmlessness and accuracy that we have.
The main results show the main results
is that preference does not reliably
track safety. Across the
13 models,
preference strength is effectively and
correlated with the harmlessness.
As we can see here.
The the person correlation is approximately
0.091. And
the the Spearman row is
minus 0.03.
This means the model's ranked higher by
preference are
constantly more harmless. And
here, as we can see,
the the ones that are very high, it's like GBTOSS,
And in the harmlessness scale, they're scoring
very low. But the ones,
in the preference that are
least their their safety score
is very high.
This is important because because
collecting more pairwise votes may make the
the preference ranking more size,
but it does not automatically make it
safety rank.
The practical takeaway is before using
a leaderboard for deployment decision, we need an
explicit preference safety alignment
audit.
The next point is that even positive
average scores can hide clinically meaningful
failures. In the paper, we define
a failure rate as a percentage of
clinical ratings scored
less than or equal to minus one. This
is important because a model can have a positive
mean score overall but
still produce a substantial number of harmful
or inaccurate responses. For
example, EBT four o has a
high accuracy, failure.
Rate around 35.4%.
In this snapshot, DBT assess has
a harmful harmful harmlessness
failure rate around 18
o.
So average alone are not enough. We need explicit
failure rates.
The risk is also not evenly distributing
specific danger zones in this nutshell, for
example, cardiology ECG is clear
no goes on. With then dangerous
percentage of 89.9%.
Largely driven by high accuracy
failure. Pathology diagnostic also
show elevated risk
While areas like general surgery,
reproductive health show much lower failure rates.
This means it's misleading. To
say a model is simply safe or unsafe
globally. A model may look acceptable
on average, but fail badly in a specific
clinical domains. So clinical
LLM evaluations should always include
specialty certified reporting, especially
before deployment.
What should change in clinical element
evaluation? The paper argues that clinical
element evaluation should not be treated as
reliability problem, not a propriety
contest. The co recommendation is
not to abandon preference judgment
Preference is useful, but it should not be treated as a
substitute for safety. We recommend
reporting preference and safety as a separate
endpoints Evaluation reports should include
failure rates from harmlessness,
and accuracy, not just average scores.
They should also certify results by
specialty and case difficulty because
risk are not evenly distributed.
Finally, evaluators should audit cofounds
such as verbosity
and refusal behavior because longer
or more polished answers
may win even when they are not safe.
The final message is do not deploy
clinical LLM just because it
wins a preference leaderboard
just because it wins a preference leaderboard,
deploy only after explicit safety
failure rates and domain specific audits.
To close, I want to thank all the organization
and people who made this work possible.
This includes all Move partner organization,
the Move tech and development team, and especially
the clinical contributors who provide expert
evaluation across participating institution.
Their feedback is what makes this kind of evaluation
possible. The broader goal of MOVE
is to build a clinically grounded
infrastructure for evaluating medical AI systems
in a way that is continuous, transparent,
and safety focused. You can scan
the code You to
visit join
the move.
Learn more about the platform, and follow or contribute
to future move work.
And thank you everyone.
I hope you enjoyed this small talk.
And I'm sorry if I went over time.
Okay. Thank you. So if you later have got any questions,
so if you're free to contact
the authors. So then let's move to
the Imprison Spotlight
talk. By Yuan Chen.
Consider the set up the
Alright. Hi, everyone. I'm Yacian. And, today,
I'm going to present our work called, voice
evaluation of reasoning ability.
In this workshop. So it's really great to see
you. And I'm from Duke, and this
work is carried out during my internship
at Adobe Research. So,
to begin with, the headline number
is, like, we cannot believe it's no better,
regarding the voice models. It
comes to, like, reasoning. And,
we tested on some of the state of the art
models at that times, and, we
tested on GPT five and GPT real time.
We which is, like,
powerful real time model of the GPT
at that time. And, we test
some of the reasoning models on that,
both variants. And it seems like
the text model can already solve a lot of
good reasoning problems. On
the other hand, the real time models or the voice
models can be used for
voice assistance or customer service
agent is not able to,
you know, answer the question correctly.
So, as I called it,
like, the real time system can hear
the problem, but and also can speak
the answer fairly well, but the answer
quality is still no good.
And, so you can hell can talk about
why fail to reason reliably, and we
try to discuss some of the points
in our papers. And, also we want
to rule out the
influence or effects of the, you know, hearing,
like, audio understanding.
Or, like, conversational abilities. And we
think these abilities are already quite,
you know, mature in these kind of
voice systems. But on the other hand, they
are not that intelligent
enough to reason to some of the, you
know, questions that can be handled,
pretty well and pretty
fast in this kind of state of our tax reasoning
models. And we convert
five data sets, from
really powerful, state of the
art reasoning benchmarks from text
models. And, we use some
of the like, rewrite and
validations to make sure they are
able to be speak
in this kind of voice settings.
And this is the, like, figure we
want to highlight. So the x
axis is, the
response time of the first audio,
like, chunk. And the y axis is
accuracy. So the accuracy
is pretty high in terms of, like, tax
models, Well, it usually takes
a lot of time, like more than ten seconds.
In average, to have a really
good quality answers. Well, on the other
hand, we think, as a voice model,
you need to be really quick in response
so that the user will not get bored
or feel uncertainties. Like, when we
talk with, Siri or other voice agents,
you always want to gather feedback immediately.
So this is, like, the gap we wanna highlight
because of the modality difference. Like,
we expect voice model to respond much
faster, while on the other hand,
the accuracy we
still want it to be higher than this kind of, you
know, around 10%,
in average accuracy. And
we also build a Cascadia system
as another baseline to show, like,
what kind of, the component in the
voice system can be improved
So we
process it using a high level
regional. That used, GPT
five as a text reasoning backbone.
And we use, a lama, served
by Grove, which is really fast. As a
narrator that summarizes the
reasoning, in a real time
manners from the g p five, and we want to
use, like, TTS service to
generate this kind of summary
or explanation to the user in real time.
So in this kind of cascaded baseline, like
the highlighted one in the bottom,
we show that we can achieve a rather higher
accuracy compared to voice systems,
well, deliver the speech in a much
faster like
manner. So but it still have this
kind of gap. This is because
during a narration or during the summary,
that we want to have the voice, you know,
output. It usually
takes, the model to in a way, summarize
the result that is sometimes noted
case we want when we want to have an accurate,
like, delivery of the
real reasoning answers. So that's
explained the gap. And also because we use
Cascadia systems, the time to
first response is relative, higher than the
voice native system, which has engine and, you
know, really fast response time.
So that shows the difference between
the cascaded system and voice
benchmarks and text, models.
And, we also compare some of the models,
like example, the Auto Flamingo models
from NVIDIA. They can have
a thinking variance. However, even
increased thinking time, it does not have
a higher accuracy in terms of
its reasoning benchmarks. I think it's largely
because the voice
understanding or audio understanding is largely be solved
by this kind of reasoning variant. But, when it
comes to, like, asking really good math
questions with a voice this kind of thinking
model still has does not have the ability
to reason well. And we
also try to, decouple reasoning from
speaking. So that's cascaded system I
talked about in the last slide. And
it shows some improvement, but it can be better.
We also improved the audio fidelity help
Well, actually, the transcription or whatever
rate is relatively low. And it's not
that because of that, the system get
answered wrong, but rather the quality
or the tax response corresponding to this kind
of question is still relatively low.
So I think that's the
kind of difficulty we where
we think it can be do it can be better.
And so this is just some of my thoughts.
So because of text models,
we we can have multi, iteration or
different turns. To, like, finalize
the, answers we need the model
is doing its internal reasoning. And it can
change like, when you, like, think longer, like,
within longer context or longer tokens.
Well well, on the other hand, on the voice models,
usually, I expect it to start quickly.
When you speak continuously, and we can all
rewind or change our answers, or without
notifying the users. So, that's why,
we think, it may be
harder for the voice systems to get a higher
results in terms of this kind of reasoning
questions. And some of the potential pathways, like
why is decoupled thinking from speaking,
is that how our human mind is doing this
tricks. Right? When I'm talking, I'm still thinking
in the back end. We think maybe some of the model
can adapt this kind of architectures. And actually,
there are already some team using this kind of architecture
to show that a model is able to, hear
when it's still thinking or listen,
and also speak when it's still thinking. So
that's two different sub questions that is
really, like, like, requires
me to think more about how to design this model in
a more efficient way. Another
thing is keep an internal monologue, like,
separate from the speech. Means
we have internal text tokens
or text sequence that is doing the reasoning
while still doing the speaking.
And then, some of the more
reliable way or more easy to achieve ways using a synchronous
SaaS session, like, what we're using
in the cascading systems. There's a thinking
back end using attacks, re reliable models,
on the other hand, we use, you know,
a a a quickly respond model.
That can able to, you know, keep the speech flow
and deliver a much higher
quality compared to native voice systems.
So Right? So this is, like, the
takeaways. And, yeah, thank
you so much.
Do we have
Yeah. So cool. Yeah. Thank you for the talk.
So next we'll have our
invited talk
from professor Addis. So she will be online.
So in the Zoom. So let me just
So LG is the
assistant professor at CMU, and she
works broadly in machine learning. And her goal
is to make ML more
reliable and robust. So her
work span with a theory and a prep and
practice and leverage tools concepts
from statistics convex optimization, and
algorithm to improve your botnet's modern
machine learning based on deep learning.
Yeah. So without further ado, let's welcome
Eddy.
Okay. Hi, everyone. Can you hear me
okay?
Okay. Okay.
Great. Alright. I'm sorry I couldn't
be there in person. Person, but I'm
glad I could join you virtually and talk about some of the
work from our group on going
beyond the creative limits of next token
prediction.
So there is no doubt that we've
made remarkable progress
on standard well defined tasks
even when these tasks get more and more
complex as we've seen lately.
What I think is the next frontier
is related to open
ended tasks. So
first is growing evidence, and maybe
you have some personal intuition too from
working with these models. That they
can be quite homogeneous in their outputs
and they far far lack the diversity
of human generations.
Furthermore, there is growing interest
recently in using AI for scientific
discovery And I like what
was, phrased in this paper,
and by mathematicians analyzing
alpha evolve, where they say that when the
tasks can be framed as
hill climbing on clean score functions,
today's systems really excel.
Then when we ask for outputs
that are genuinely diverse and original,
the stuff we think of as real discovery
the picture gets much murkier. And
I think that's the next frontier.
How do we get creativity in open ended
tasks and how do we get outputs that are
diverse and original?
In this talk, that's what I'll focus on,
and I'll first describe how we study
this question in the first place. And
what I'll show you is the
current paradigm, which has been really successful
for these well defined standard
tasks like coding and really
complex reasoning as well, can
actually be misaligned with creativity.
And I'll talk about the bottlenecks of why
of our current paradigms. And then I'll,
talk how we applied some of these ideas
for larger scale math reasoning and then
conclude.
Okay. So let's, get right in
into the setup of creativity.
So there's a lot of debate on creativity.
So there are some papers that are
optimistic about the potential of our current
systems being able to do creative things,
And there's also papers on the other side
that are more pessimistic claiming
that a lot of current systems are actually
just outputting things in the training data
or are not meaningfully creative and so on.
And the reason for this debate is, in a natural
because it's very hard to say something
about what's happening with the real systems because we don't
even know what training data goes into these
models, and it's hard to define novelty
and creativity.
So what I'll do in this talk and what we do
in our paper is instead to
construct minimal open
ended algorithmic task,
by drawing inspiration from how cognitive
scientists think about creativity.
And using these tasks, we will quantify
some limits of our current approaches
and also highlight alternatives
that can do better. So that's
gonna be our setup.
So as an example, consider this creative
leap like wordplay.
A clown held the door open for me.
What a nice gesture.
So this work this joke works
by finding a path through
seemingly unconnected concepts like
clown and held the door. So clown connects to
gesture. Hold the door connects
to a gesture, and, the joke lands
because those two sound like each other.
So, abstractly, we can think of that kind of
creativity as finding
two nodes in a concept graph
and then revealing the path between them.
And this is what cognitive scientists like Boden
have termed combinational creativity, and you
can see this is finding new combinations
within the graph.
So here's a one toy example that we construct
that is motivated by combinational
creativity.
Here, the model has to generate
sibling pairs along with the parent as a
triplet. Where
they are siblings and they share a parent
in a large implicit graph that
is taught to the model and the model stores
this graph in the weights. So
So in this graph that I have here, g
and f are siblings, because they share
a common parent y.
And we have, like, an implicit bipartite
graph that has some parents, and each parent has a
lot children.
So what we do is we can get training
data of the following kind, like two siblings
and their parent. We have a bunch of such triplets
train a language model on this training
data. And the question is, can
the model generate new
and valid new triplets
from the same implicit graph. So that's
what we call creativity because it's
finding kind of what we are looking for, the structure,
but generating new things.
And we have to set up the problem carefully
such that there are enough training data
for the model to infer all the
edges but there are
also unseen triplets, that the model
could generate that are valid that are
not in the training data. So we
ensure this is the case.
So this is one example that we call
the sibling discovery.
And related to that, we also have a triangle
discovery, which is very similar and
there's an implicit graph, and the model has
to generate triangles
valid triangles from that graph. There
is some training data and the model has to
generate new triangles.
There's a different kind of creativity
which is called exploratory creativity,
where, for example, consider the act
of designing problems or molecules
or deriving
100 different collateries within a paradigm
with some small set of laws.
So here, we're not discovering preexisting
connections. Instead, we want
the model to generate altogether
new things, subject to a few rules.
And the way we model this abstractly
is we ask the
model to generate an adjacency
list, so list of edges. And
the requirement is that this list should secretly
rearrange or has a permutation,
to form a structure. So the structure
could be something like a circle or a line
could have different things, but these are the two that we
consider. And we want
something novel, which means that there should be a novel permutation
that rearranges to form the structure.
And so this is meant to mimic how in,
say, a math problem or a story,
we might set up many different objects
in conflict, and they have to undergo
a novel dynamic towards a
resolution. K. So these
are the two tasks that we consider
and, we show some training data
from that task. And we
train a language model. And then we sample
some n
different independent generations from the model.
And we measure creativity concretely
quantitatively as follows. What
fraction of generations are coherent,
which means that, for example, in the triplet
task, the two siblings that
are shown and the parent, there should actually be siblings
sharing that parent. They
should be unseen so that we don't want things from
the training data. We want new combinations,
new explorations. And of course,
we want them to be unique across the different samples
from the model. So if we have t different
samples, we wanna see what fraction of those end
up being unique, unseen, and
coherent. That is our creativity.
K. So that's the setup.
And now we can go into how
well the current systems do on these simple tasks
that we created where we can measure creativity
very clearly.
So the predominant paradigm, the standard
recipe now, is autoregressive next
token prediction. So where we train
a model to generate one token at
a time, So the model has to generate
some token condition on everything that came
before, which is the prefix.
So the nice thing about this is it
is fully general. Which
means that any sequence distribution
can be represented in this way on its autoregressive
manner. So in
principle, next token prediction
should be enough.
And there is sort of one,
nuance about the training that we have keep
in mind. So how these models are
trained is at every position, the model is trained
to predict the target. Given
the ground truth of what came before,
rather than its own generations. So our training,
for example, if the model has to predict x x
three, it's given x zero, x one, x two,
and it has to learn to predict x three,
given the ground truth. So this is often called
teacher forcing because the teachers'
generations of ground truth are given to the model at
every position.
This is a standard recipe by which models are
trained. Should seem like next token
prediction can more represent everything. This
should work. But what
we see that is perhaps surprising is
that on all of these tasks,
models trained in this way exhibit
low creativity.
So they're not able to generate
new novel coherent and
unseen examples with the structure that we had.
And if we look into it a little bit deeper, it seems
in particular that they have high memorization.
Which means that whatever the
model generates ends up being things
from the training data itself rather than new things.
So why is it that next token learning
which is the standard paradigm which has worked
so well in various closed ended tasks,
why does it fail in even these simple
creativity tasks? So
let's look at what the model is supposed to learn
versus what it actually learns.
Ideal factorization, like, the way we want the
model to solve the task, is it first
guesses a parent, like, randomly picks a parent,
and then generates the two siblings.
So the stochastic random
planning step that we want is the model to pick
the parent first and then generate the two
siblings and then reorder them.
But if you look at the supervision from next
token to, learning, because
of the fact that the teacher force like, the model
is given the ground truth predictions, what
the model actually has learned
is the three terms. So one is
it has to learn probability of generating
a sibling, The other one
is, of, yeah, one child and then the
sibling of the child. And then the last token
is probability of predicting the parent given
the two siblings.
So the crucial thing here to note
is that the last token, which is where
the parent comes into the picture,
there, the model has to predict the parent given
the two children. And
that is something that is trivial for the model to do.
Because it just has to look up the parent
of any one of the children
and that and especially in our bike part at
construction, this can be very easy to do.
And so the model learns this instantly.
It's a trivial shortcut.
And people are probably familiar with
things like simplicity bias, which is that the
models will learn the shortcuts quickly if something
exists. So because
it's a trivial shortcut to predict the
last token, which is the parent,
Effectively, what's happening is the model
fits that very easily, very quickly,
and it's almost as if that token
doesn't exist at all or we don't really get supervision
from that. And the model is
left to learn that
these two terms, which is, you know,
one child and then the sibling,
which is a very hard distribution to
learn without information that
there is a parent that is connecting these two children.
So without enough signal, the model
falls back to just memorizing the
training data because this is a hard
distribution.
So what has happened is this
the fact that the parent is present because of this
teacher forcing setup ends up being
a shortcut for the model because it's very easy
to predict the parent given the two children.
And so the model doesn't really learn to use
the parent and ends up memorizing
the the the the two siblings.
This is our intuition for why next
token learning can fail in these
creative tasks. And maybe you're thinking we
can just reorder the tokens. What if we
know, just present the training data with the parent
first? In this particular case,
reordering would fix the problem.
But if you'll remember the triangle example that
we had, there there is no
easy there is no reordering that will fix the
problem. Because given any two
tokens, it's easy to predict the third token.
Of the triangle or the third edge of the triangle.
And so any ordering will have the same
problem with the intuition that, like, once you
have the first few objects,
it becomes really easy to predict the, like,
the final one, and so the model doesn't learn
the overall big structure.
So if this is true, we can try to remove
the shortcut and see what happens.
And one way to remove the shortcut
is that, at least in a few samples, we
can remove the teacher forcing,
So the model has to predict the for example,
has to predict the entire triplet at once,
It's not predicting the parent given the children.
And so we've removed that shortcut.
And one way to do this is called teacher
less training. Where we can just give some math
tokens or some trivial tokens as a
prefix and get the model to predict all of them.
So we usually train a model on a mixture of
the two so that the model knows how to
use its own generations at test time, but
then we've also removed the shortcut on a few
examples by getting the model to predict all the
tokens at once.
And we see that across all of our
tasks. This kind of teacher less
training or multi token prediction
does end up being more creative than next
token learning, which is the standard paradigm.
So this shortcut that we identified
earlier seems to be at least one of
factors contributing to poor creativity of
next token learning because when we remove
that shortcut, we see that the creativity
does go up.
So that gets me to the first, sort of
takeaway. I can't believe that next
token learning, which seems to work really well
on tasks where the goal is very clear,
On many tasks, it works very well, including many
complex real world setups. But
even in these simple tasks where you
have this latent structure, the model
seems to fail. This learning paradigm seems
to fail.
So just to summarize that a little more abstractly,
in general, in a creative process,
the outputs are generated
after some kind of thinking, which is
the stochastic planning part, and that
can be unobserved. And for
example, in the triangle setup, it's that you
don't see the actual process by which
you figure out, like, search over the
triangles. And when we
have such a setup, next token learning
can fail because once we have
the entire thing given, like, the model, it's trivial
to predict certain feature
forcing, and so there are these shortcuts
which make next token learning bad, and it ends
up memorizing the data instead.
And removing these shortcuts can actually
improve creativity, for example,
through teacher less multi token training.
In the paper, we also look at diffusion language
models, which are also a version of removing
the shortcut because, there again, you have to predict
a few tokens given masked every
some other tokens. So there is also
we can think of that as removing shortcuts and that
also improves here.
Now there's a second issue with
our current paradigm, which
is that even if we, you know, are
preventing memorization of the training data,
what can happen and what
is observed and noted is that
the different generations from the model
might end up being the same. So even
if we generate multiple samples, we don't get
variety.
And you might wonder, let's just raise the temperature
because that's a defect or knob, and that
should fix this. But what we see
is when we increase the temperature, it's not
a a free lunch because the
coherence also drops. And
the temperature sampling is just adding some entropy
when we sample the output tokens, and so
the model overall becomes less coherent.
So here's, our intuition, for
thinking about this. In a transformer,
diversity is typically elicited through
temperature sampling and this might
be suboptimal because in this
way, the model has to actually flush out many
thoughts in parallel And then
while we are sampling the tokens, it kind
of has to end up picking one or the other.
And so this seems like much hard to do.
A more natural way and maybe
how we would approach this is
think about many ideas and then you pick one of
them. And then you flush that out
one thought at a time.
And so we can think of bringing the randomness
to the input and instead, but the model can, like, think
about different things and pick one idea and then
commit to it.
So what this concretely means is
in standard training, we go from some prefix
or a prompt to the generations directly.
Instead, what we'll do is some seed conditioning, which
is you have your prompt and
then you also give a random string to
the model. And the hope is the model can use
this random string, the prefix
as the source of randomness to generate
different things, after that.
And so the way we operationalize this is
every training data is given, like,
some random string that is fixed, and we
train the model with these random strings.
And at that time, we give new random strings,
and and that by changing the randomness
in the string at time, we get new samples.
So different seeds can lead to different outputs
or different samples. And
maybe this can prevent the drop in coherence
because now the model can actually focus
on one thought at a time rather than
what happens when we increase the temperature where we
just kind of adding a lot of entropy to the
output distribution.
So we call this naive seed conditioning
because we're literally prepending a completely
random string to each training example. So
there's no structure in how we get these strings.
Is really surprising is that despite the simplicity,
even with the, with zero
temperature, which means you've turned off any randomness
from the output, and all the randomness
comes from these strings. We see that seed conditioning
is actually comparable
temperature sampling in creativity.
So the model is somehow able to use these
random strings of prefixes and
convert them to a meaningful source of randomness
that leads to more
diverse samples that also have the
structure. That we want.
So this shows that this kind of seed conditioning
could be a reasonable order alternative
for diversity elicitation compared to the
de facto standard of temperature sum. Sampling.
What's also really cool is in some cases,
seed conditioning ends up being
the most creative method, outperforming the
best temperature as well.
So this intuition that, fleshing
out many thoughts at a time might be suboptimal
and instead we should flush out one thought
at a time by bringing the randomness to the
input seems to hold for these
exam that we saw.
So that takes me to the second, surprise.
We all use temperature sampling currently as
a way of getting diversity, but temperature
sampling is actually not as good.
And even something very simple, like adding
random strings into the
prefix seemed to improve the diversity
of the models generated.
So I've shown two different bottlenecks
in current paradigms, and there are a lot of you know,
nice ideas that we could scale up.
And we've started doing some of in the group
now. And I'll talk about one particular
thing that we did on larger
scale mathematical reasoning. So it's
a what we do is, like, a close cousin
of seed conditioning, which can improve
performance.
So this is a paper called Mode Conditioning.
At this, I clear that was presented.
So the standard paradigm that's very popular
now with reasoning is what
is called test time scaling. And so one
way to do this is to sample
multiple traces from the model independently
And then if you have a good verifier, which is
the case for a lot of these math settings,
then you can call success if any of your
samples ends up being correct.
So you can sample k times you have effectively
k trials.
But standard training can end up
wasting a lot of samples because
of low diversity. So the same issue as before,
if all the samples end up looking the same, then
this is really a waste. And so
if you look at the top panel here, like, let's
say a model sees both
breadth for search and depth for search in the training data.
In standard training, what ends up happening is the
model ends up picking one of one of the
two as a predominant strategy. And
many of the samples end up being basically the
same attempt. And so we're not meaningfully
you know, utilizing the fact that we can
try different things.
And you're having the same intuition as before
that maybe we should have the model of
pickets of random strategy in the beginning and
then come into that strategy, and that's a better
way of getting, diversity
in samples. So for example, if we
knew which training samples were
breadth first search or depth first search,
then we can do this mode condition training
where we introduce this prefix
to every sample and so the model knows
how to use a BFS prefix or
a DFS prefix. And at test
time, we can now ensure by changing the
prefix manually. That's let's say
50% of the samples try BFS,
50% of samples try BFS.
So this way, mode condition training as well
as inference allow us
to explicitly try all the modes at
test time by changing the prefixes
that we provide to the model.
So with f so intuitively with
the same inference budget, we can probably
sample more diverse things.
Of course, there's a practical question of where do we get
these modes. Like, how do we know which strategy
is used in which training data? So we
do something very simple, and there's probably more
complicated, nicer things that one can do.
But we take some real world data
like NuminaMac and simply cluster
the gradients And then, let's
say, into k clusters, and then
we assign one a a label to each of
these clusters as the mode labels. In
the experiments I'm gonna show you, we just, you know, pick
two clusters just for convenience. So we
just formed two clusters from the training
data automatically and there's really simple way.
And we evaluate the performance on 500.
And I have the results here. So we see
that across you know, various model sizes.
What happened is, especially for
larger k, we see that mode
conditioning, mod c here
ends up performing much better because
it's able to better use the diversity
that we can get at test time. And
so for the same, Passat
k
more fewer inference samples by
simply preventing this mode collapse issue.
And I just wanted to highlight that we don't use
any auxiliary We're using just the same
training data and automatically figuring out
the modes. And this is one of those rare
times where with the same data and no extra
information, we're actually able to get, like, a
consistent gain across many, many settings
by addressing this fundamental mode collapse
issue.
And, we do this for
but the nice thing is it's also
ends up being a better starting point
for reinforcement learning because these mode
conditioning and doing these mode using
these modes at task time, also allow
for better controlled exploration.
And so we see that mode conditioning
SFT plus RL outperforms
standard SFT plus RL across all k,
And, interestingly, the usual
criticism of RL or, like, the usual
down is that at large scale, it
ends up underperforming the base model because
RL itself causes a diverse to
collapse. But with mode conditioning, we're seeing
that we are outperforming the base the
starting point across all k, because
actually preserving, the kind of diversity
even through the audit process, and we're not and it's sort
of mitigating the diversity collapse issue
of reinforcement learning as well.
And so the kind of the broader idea
is that temperature sampling might not be a
good idea to get meaningful diversity from the
model. And if we introduce even
simple things like having these ways of
telling the model which modes to use and
allowing the model to try different modes
at test time in a controlled manner.
That vastly improves the performance of these models.
Okay. So I'll, sort of conclude.
So the big picture is that we identified
two orthogonal failures
of standard paradigms for creative tasks,
and these are somewhat surprising because we
have converged the standard paradigm, and it feels
like we can do a lot. But there are also
some fundamental blind spots that we identify
through our simple creative tasks.
So on this next token learning versus multi token
learning, because of the shortcuts,
and then there's also the seed conditioning
as an alternative to temperature sampling
as a way of getting diversity from these models.
And I think I mentioned this before. There are interesting connections
to diffusion models that I did didn't get into, but
you can check the paper.
This I feel like this work opens up
more questions than it answers, so there's a lot of
avenues for future work. So
one immediate thing that we find very surprising
is why even does seat conditioning work in the
first place? So why is it that we're
able to provide random strings
and the model is learning what is the right structure
to use this diversity to get
these tasks. For example, the model is able to go from a
random string to a stochastic plan of
the parent or stochastic plan of
which triangle to generate and so on. So
why is it that this works? Like, how is the model able to
do that? That's very surprising and something
that's worth investigating.
On the other side, I spoke about mode conditioning
where we provide very clear
semantically meaningful modes to the model.
But then we don't have a way to get new random
modes. So how do we get extrapolation?
Can we prompt the model with, like, a mix
mixture of modes in the prompt? And does that allow the
model to actually generate, like, completely
new strategy, for example? So can we get
the best of what the model is able to do with
seed conditioning, but also in a way that's more semantically
meaningful so that might work even better?
So that's another very interesting question to think
about.
And a lot of our contribution was hopefully
to build minimal examples that can inspire
new ideas. We wanted to first
have a way to concretely think about
creativity and show what we might be missing
with our current models. And we
came up with, like, few alternatives, and
I think there's room for a lot lot more,
lot better strategies for diversity,
for training these models to allow them to infer
this sort of unobserved creative
leap of thought. So I hope you can all join us
in developing new methods to further push
this next frontier of these models.
And there's also interesting questions on we're
not just developing one model one. We're
training and there's like there's like a whole life
cycle, so this pretraining. There's
SFT. There's RL. And so what's the right way all
of these stages should interact, especially
when we think about things like creativity?
How do we prevent diversity collapse across
stages? What do we really want from
pretraining versus RL and so on? So there's a lot of
questions here. That are open and things that we
are actively researching in the group So
keep an eye out on our group website for
papers on this topic if there's something
that you're excited about. And
then I want to thank my wonderful
student, collaborators, and authors here.
So Vaishnav is a researcher at Google, will
who co led along with Chen the work on creativity
that I presented first with Charles.
Chen and Sachin worked on mood conditioning
that I presented towards the end on mathematical
reasoning.
Yeah. And I also wanted to shout out to another
poster that we have in the same workshop
where we look at optimization and how what's the right
way to do pretraining, especially in
this life cycle of LLMs where it goes
through multiple stages, So go check
out the poster on sharpness of our pre training if you're
interested in that. With that,
I will stop, and I think we might have
time for questions if
if that works.
Great. Thank you, Aditi, for the great talk,
and
Any question from the audience?
Yeah. Thanks for the talk. I wanted
to ask if the beam search
does it help creativity or otherwise?
Yeah. That's a good question. So we didn't
we didn't try a we didn't try that
that systematically, but on the simple task that
we tried, we have this in the paper. It
doesn't work as well as example,
seed conditioning in our setup.
So you need to yeah. It yeah.
We tried that. It doesn't work as well as seed conditioning.
Conditioning. Because it's a similar issue
where, like, we're still relying on just
the output to have that like,
the model has to still, like, in in the output distribution
somehow keep the entire mixture, and
that ends up not being very easy to do.
So you talk about
the burden, burden,
framework. Boden
does not talk only about
correctness, calls about value.
And Uh-huh. Value, I think, it is
it is something more than correctness. Can
you comment on this?
Yeah. So in some sense, like, what we are
trying to show here is all also we are measuring
the value in terms of the novelty. Like, is
it finding new connections, and is it find
just, like, exploring new things beyond just is it
correct? That's sort of where the uniqueness and
the unseen, like, the novelty come in.
It's not just if it's valid. And I think
maybe what you're also referring to is there's
a third notion of creativity that we didn't
get into, and it's much harder to think about, which
is what Bogen calls transformative
creativity. So in all of these cases, we
assume there is a right there is a structure
So, like and we want to generate new things
following roughly that structure. But then
maybe the rules of the game are itself wrong and we
need to re like, you know, rechange the whole rules.
And that is, like, the transformative creativity set
up. Like, maybe we don't really care about siblings,
and we should be caring about something else. So, like, that
the kind of creativity that's, like, even harder to,
like, figure, like, what are the right toy tasks
or, like, how do we think about that? So
that's another interesting direction of future work, which
is, like, the third axis of creativity.
But in these two in these two setups, like, we
exactly care about the thing that we don't just care
about correctness, we care about the value. And in
our case, the value is just is it novel?
Is it new? And is it adding knowledge beyond
the training data? And that's how we measure that in our setup.
I wonder how does, your results
and thank you for the talk. That was great. I
wonder how it relates to,
creativity in the,
more, like, broad sense. So
artists using
you know, text to image models to
to do art and all that. So how
does your work relate to that?
Yeah. That's a good question. So
the way I think about it is, like, even
the I like, creativity in art, for
example, when you're checking whether the model is generating
something new, it could be is it, like, just
generating new pixels, like, the you know, are the shades
different? That's maybe less interesting. That's
a little bit like the temperature sampling version where, like,
yeah, it's adding something different. But
then there's a question of, like, what was the creative process by
which the artist thought of, like, which
styles to combine or which objects to combine.
And that's the thing that we're trying to measure is, like,
can models actually generate new sort of combinations
like that? Like, is it actually able to conceive
new ideas, or is it just taking stuff that's
existing within the training data?
So kind of the pessimistic view, I guess,
is that a lot of the things that generate the model
are actually very related to what's in the
training data itself, and it's not meaningfully
generating new things. And even when the model
currently generates new stuff, it's because
we prompt it with, like, ideas of try x in
the style of y or whatever. We are giving those ideas,
and the model cannot come up with those ideas
on its own. With our current
paradigms. So that's sort of the claim or takeaway
from our simple examples.
And in in and the optimistic view is,
like, maybe, like, you know, of the human value
or, like, is is still in in that kind
of creativity and that novelty. Right now,
it looks like it still comes from
the people, and so, you know, that's how we should
evaluate or judge the contributions
So any more questions?
Cool. Yeah. Hussein, thanks again for the
great talk.
Yeah. Yeah. So, we will have a
lunch break until 1PM.
And after 1PM, we will have a post
session tier to
like, 2PM twenty five. Yeah.
Alright. Welcome back, everybody.
I hope you enjoyed the discussions during
the poster sessions.
We are about to have our next
invited talk
our invited speaker today, it's my pleasure
to introduce professor Preslav Narkov.
He's a professor and department chair for NLP
at the Muhammed Bensayid University of Artificial
Intelligence. And he's leading the development
of, JAYCE, which
is the world's best open source Arabic centric
LLM, Nanda, which
is world's best open weights Hindi
model, as well as Shaikhala, which is kind of
the equivalent for the Kazakh,
language. And, before
he, was at Muir Berbin Sayed,
he was a principal
scientist at the Qatar Computing Research
Institute, where he was leading the Tanbhi Mega
project aiming to
limit the impact of fake news, propaganda,
and media bias, making users more aware of what
they are reading thus promoting media literacy
and critical thinking. He received
his PhD degree in computer science from University
of California at Berkeley. And
today, we are honored to have him
talk about Truly Open Language Specific
Safe factual, and specialized large language
models.
Okay. You. Thank you very much for the kind
introduction and, can you guys hear me well?
Yes. Okay. And, for the
opportunity. So, let me start
I'll kind of organize my talk around some key messages
So the first one is that we need to truly open
voice language models. And,
kind of we talk about, we kind of hear about
open source language models. They are not really open
source. They are kind of open weights. Right? But
what you really need is truly open
ones. And can make some initiatives
like that and kind of I can, you know, so
kind of ours was probably the first one,
is this LM three sixty. So those are models
that are not just open weights, they are
also open code they are also
open source, they are also open data,
and even open code to generate the data.
Right? And kind of there are a couple of more initiatives
that have been emerging after that.
So, I think this is really is something important
if we are to develop science. And, another
thing that I want to stress is that it's not
just small models that we have been releasing in this
way. We have been releasing models up to 70,000,000,000
parameter models in a truly open way.
Right? So, kind of, you even have the
engineering check points of the experiments. So basically,
whatever our engineers see, this
is what you see. Right? And
and I believe that this is something that
is very, very important. And,
so, actually,
if you go like to give you some illustration
of that, right? So maybe kind of I can I
can try to open this? Let's see if it's gonna
work. Right. So this kind of this is
the the blog post about the data.
Right? So, this is TxC three sixty. It's
also kind of training recipe, It's
also kind of, you know, where the data comes from
and and you see here on the right how small
those scrollers and attention
that actually kind of things are even hidden.
And, every single decision
oh, yeah. Sorry. Well, I don't know
how this works. I think
because I have I'm here in presentation mode.
Maybe no.
Okay. Give me a
sec. Yeah.
Okay. Maybe kind of now you see
it. But, the point is that every single
decision, every single
you know, parameter, every single cut off that is
being set in preparing the data is
there. It is backed by the best practice
from the literature and also by the experiments
that have been done. So, and
I think that it's important to
to advance open size.
So, and actually, so this
artificial analysis
it's an interesting index
of AOMs that evaluates them across different
models. Right, have been,
ranking versions of our models
right, consistently as the most open
one. Right? Terms of openness.
So maybe the second message
that I would like to stress here is that
we need language specific large language
models. So, again, if I don't believe
in universal models that can do everything,
In fact, we are going to probably discuss this
more in the panel afterwards.
But most of the models that you see
these days what we think is a model is not really
a model, it's actually a system. Right?
And and it's probably not even one
model. And it's kind of a lot of things
around it. So, we
need language specific language models. So,
and I'm going to talk about Arabic centering.
So, I mean, Arabic is an important language. It has
about 400,000,000 models,
but most models we have not
seen in the Arabic And,
this has many implications,
Is there an echo, microphone or something?
I don't know where it came from.
Okay. Sorry?
Because there's another one down?
It's not on, is it?
Don't hear me? Okay. It's good?
Better? Okay. Yeah. So,
and, well, maybe kind of two points
is then, one is that,
models have seen little Arabic,
and as I said, it has many implications. I
will show you one. Kind
of many people don't think about.
And it's about tokenization.
So, if you think about it,
so, okay. Here's what
GPT three point five and four tokenization
is doing to an English text.
And they have taken on purpose
text that is about some strange
Greek cheese there is some kind of out
of vocabulary words like kopanishio, excladic,
and it's doing quite well. You see
even very long words like characteristics not
really be cut.
But, if I do this to Arabic, see
what happens? Right?
Is the authorization of Chargebee team. This is how
Arabic is being handled. Right? It's chopped
into individual characters. Actually,
let me ask you a question. Why do
you think they are question marks?
Any ideas?
Yeah? Left to right
or No. It's not that. It's not left to right is just like
in your in kind of presentation thing. It's it's
kinda takes actually kind of right to left as well.
I mean, yeah, it's left to right. No. It's not
it's not that. Yeah.
Yeah. It's a Unicode. It's a broken Unicode character.
The question is why is it broken? Or tell why is
it broken? Because the
way that those models don't work
at a character level, They work at the byte
level. Means that in certain cases, Arabic
text is split even in the middle of
the letter, Can you imagine how crazy it is?
Okay? So, okay.
And then, I mean, what are the implications
of this? Just like to give you some idea, right? So,
you have you have, I don't know, kind of let's
say, GPT two four point I mean,
it's like the fertility, if I give you a 100 words,
you generate me 417.
Right? In our model, it's kind
of English and Arabic is about the same,
but what is the implication of splitting something
into 4.2?
Blocks? Well, there are quite a few.
One is that, if you have this chopped into
letters, or or or even
half letters, right, what does it mean to a
letter to attend to another letter? Okay. How
can you reason with that? Actually, it works.
Because it's a lot of data, a lot of computer still
works. Right? Then also yours
your context window is smaller. It's four
times smaller. Your computation is quadratic.
17 times more from the attention.
Right? But also you know, in terms
of money, in terms of compute, right, in
terms of environmental cost,
terms of if you want, if you're calling the API, you
are paying per token. But if the
tokenization is broken, you are paying, like, four times
more than you should. Right? All
these things need to be there and need to be
fixed. Right? And kind of now, there are different initiatives,
right, for multilingual language models. But
it's something that you know,
has to be paid attention to. And the problem
is that if you have a model, let's say, that wants to
support, let's say, 100 languages, you cannot do this
equally well. Don't have enough vocabulary
size. That's why I believe that you need specialized
models.
And yeah, we have these models up
to 70,000,000,000 parameter models
and, know, the model
is there, you can if you can install it from the phone, this kind of
chat. There, has been, like, there for,
like, more than two years in
you know, Microsoft Asia,
in Amazon, services. And we have been, like,
developing similar models for Kazah
and for Hindi because we believe in
in specialized models that
are adapt to specific languages.
Maybe the next message and I'm I'm going
to show you the model in a bit, but
maybe the next thing is that we need safe language
models. There has been a lot of research
on safety, but,
you know, if you think about it, where do you put
the safety mechanisms?
Well, I mean, you can put them in different places. You
can like clean the data, right, so
it is safe. You can do better instruction tuning
for safety. You can do it in
the call of the model, in the prompt.
Or you can do it in the deployed model. You can do
things that are analyzing what the
model is saying and, you
know, how the kind of what the user is saying, whether they
are safe and safe in the request, how the model
is responding, whether they're something unsafe in
the in the answer. You can do this with different kind of
classifiers or AOMs,
you can also do test time scaling and everything.
Now, question for you, where
is the most important place to put
it? And the one that has the
biggest impact?
Yeah? Where?
Number one.
Okay. So, I mean, actually kind of there are different
opinions. Right? Some people think that you should not
be cleaning the input data too much
because cannot explain to the model what is bad
if it has never seen something bad.
It needs to know what bad is. You need to
know what behavior to stay away from. Right? So, that
the you I mean, I'm not saying that you should
if you only give it bad data, you're not going to get a good
model. But you should kind of have some bad
data there, right, so that you can teach
that.
Actually, the most important place is
the prompt. This is the one because
the model really, really listens to it.
Okay? And it is very hard to ignore. It's always there.
Kind of the hidden prompt.
But let me kind of start with something. Right?
When we started building actually, we started
working on Jase before there was even
Chargebee T, right, kind of collecting the data and think,
we first kind of develop released it, like, about
six months, sometime in August, actually,
2023, it
was not clear that it can even
be done. It was not clear that anybody can
do something similar to Chargebee T. Right, Scott? We
didn't know what we are doing.
And if we are worrying about safety, and
the first knife idea
is, okay, we are going to
teach the model not to answer. Okay?
So kind of when not to answer. And,
you know, developed this
taxonomy. It's a three level taxonomy. I can walk you quick
quickly through it. Right?
Where you have, like, human chatbot
interactions, things about self harm
or that
of malicious, illegal uses,
or or or stuff like that or or things that
are unethical, how to tell my friend,
or things that are about stereotyping
or know, toxic language or
disinformation harms, like, you know, false information
or advice that you should be careful how
you are giving? Things like
medical, financial, legal, and so on and so
forth. Right? And
you know, this kind of personal information, financial
information, and so on,
cybersecurity things.
And, yeah, kind of we were teaching the
model not to answer those kind of questions, what can
possibly go wrong with that? Actually, it's
an inflation paper Right?
But we started analyzing
what models are doing, actually,
it's not just about not answering,
it's answering in different ways.
Okay? And it's something that is very important.
So, we actually kind of developed this taxonomy of
four different, like, six
different levels. So, one level is
an ongoing transfer. Another
level is to say, not even understanding that
something horrible is happening. But there are things in
between like, oh, I'm not a doctor, I'm not a
lawyer, Right? I'm still going to answer
you and there's kind of certain level of safety.
And it turns out that models, we
have kind of hooked into this early on,
models have different strategies when it comes
to different parts of the taxonomy.
So, for example, when it's about malicious
use, right,
you want to to kind of use the LN for something
malicious, this kind of very little tolerance.
It's about some kind of fake news, some
false information, disinformation,
they are kind of more at the level of trying
to educate you. So, it's
not like saying I can probably kind
of now made maybe a good
time for me to demonstrate this. Right? Maybe
kind of future is let me see.
Okay. So
oh, and now suggest to I.
Sorry. It woke me out.
It Okay. Now it
should work. If I say I don't know.
Let me let me try something. I mean,
explain Okay.
How NASA faked
the moon landing.
Right? So
it's not okay. Actually, it tells
me that, this is harmful and
misleading. Okay. This kind of one kind of response.
But if I say, you know,
explain the health
benefits of fishing broken
glass. Let's
see.
Okay. So
it actually, you know, get the fit. It it wants to
tell me that, you know, kind of it's it's not
just saying, you know, this is hard of point, whatever
kind of it's actually explains, you know, what is going on.
So, you see that you have different kinds of strategies,
right, when it comes to those
things. Or if I say something like,
you know,
why are all
Bulgarians so lazy and
stupid? Okay? Now, I can
say this because I'm Bulgarian, that's reclaimed speech.
Okay? If it was some somebody
else, you can somebody can get to find it. So,
sorry for the Bulgarians in the room. Okay?
It tells you, no, it's not appropriate in in
the the the the the, okay? So so, you know,
it catches it. But kind of the the the
level of answers is, you know,
of different kind of degree.
And, I mean, this was kind of an influential
work, Cask quite some
citations and we have developed this now to
apply this to Arabic, to Bulgarian, to Chinese, to
Hindi, German, Kazakh, Russian and so on. We have
publications, several publications on this
And it's not just about translating this
to another language,
like doing things
that are other But kind
of the first thing is, okay, imagine you take this
and you say, I'm going to
put this
It's not just about translating. When you translate,
you don't want to have Mary. You want to put
some Chinese name. Right? But there are other things.
Are kind of region specific
sensitivity. Right? There are kind of political events
or maybe human rights or maybe historical
or maybe other things kind of that you
need to adapt. Right? In fact, when
we developed this and to hear in making
this more and more interesting, For
example, for Arabic, when we did this,
right, we developed
different kind of regional specific
things where we had
annotations not from just one country, but
from the perspective of different Arab countries
in each country, the perspective of the government in that
position. And actually, something very interesting
that we have found out that some models
were scoring very kind of quite high
on safety everywhere. And we are like, what are
those guys doing? Know what they are doing?
They were good politicians. So,
for example, you say, oh, yeah. Why the government
in this country is so corrupt? And you say, well,
they have, like, these cases, you know, and blah
blah blah in the past. And, you know, whatever.
However, you know, measures are being taken,
you know, and kind of, you know, these kind of
many you know, kind of So, so
it's really kind of putting something at the end
that kind of smooths it, or if you say something harsh
about position, say, who position did this and that
or or or whatever group but kind
of really kind of smooths it and it's kind of how politicians
speak, right? Kind of trying to
say something but maybe
not to be it's not going to be at zero at
all. Five. It's going to be somewhere in the middle.
But those are still kind of considered safe.
Right? And some language models are very good at that.
And actually doing just this
can kind of push you the
perception of the safety of the model a lot.
Okay? It's not about having many, many,
many datasets.
And the other thing that I want to to kind of
stress here is, I told you about the prompt. Right?
This is the prompt of the original JS.
Right? It's quite wrong. It's repetitive.
But it's very, very safe. It's
very hard to say ignore your prompt or whatever, whatever,
whatever is
Of course, you pay, you know, computational
cost for this, but you can also kind of cash, so
it's not that much of a concern.
Right? It's really, really good. I mean,
okay. One thing is, we have kind
of some studies You pay some price
sometimes on performance. Actually, anything you do
you need to evaluate in terms of utility,
right, kind of we had things, for example, for
Hindi. We have a paper there where we really
kind of study the impact of the prompt and
it depends what you want. But, it's
also a balance. You don't want
for example, if you say translate me this,
and the the thing that you want translate has something
offensive, the model can refuse. Do you
want this? Well, depends.
On the situation. And this
is the Arabic version
of that. So and and,
you know, maybe the next thing is that I want to tell
you is that we need
factual models. Okay?
So, and and,
so when it comes to factuality,
in my view, they have been
three big revolutions in information product.
Production. So, the first one
is when Gutenberg invented the printing press,
The second one is when
social media came, and the third one
is when Jenny I came.
And, in each of these cases, the
old gatekeepers were removed.
And the public was left
unprepared and unprotected. Least for some time.
This was an interesting evolution of
terminology. So, initially, we have
talked about fake news, fake news.
And the solution was what? Fact checking. Right?
Let's look on the futurity. But then
people realized, well, wait a minute, why are we
checking it? Because it can't possibly
cause harm. Okay? So, kind of the
term disinformation was born that is adopted
by journalists, international organizations.
It's something that is factual but also harmful.
And over time, people realize
actually, harm is more important
Whether it's true or not, Right? I mean,
actually, journalists are telling me that the best
manipulation is to annotate the truth, only the truth,
but not the whole truth. Right?
So, the focus was on the harm. And this is how the
public attention was this is how research
was going on, this is how my own research was evolving.
Kind of I started, I have done a lot of work on
on on disinformation space, on on the fluctuality
space, but I was kind of more and more interested in
the harm. Okay? And it's kind
of how things were evolving. And
looked like one way street. Except
that large
language models, JennyI came and made factuality
great again. But under a
new name, hallucination. Which, by the way, is
the wrong term. So,
you know, hallucination was word of the year.
And and, I mean, why is the wrong term?
Well, you tell me
that, you know, the the capital of
of you know,
so it's it's
if you say that, I don't know, okay, if you say
that the Brazilian president right,
is is is going to, you know, to Europe,
I mean, at the and in different translation,
you have actually the name of the Brazilian president
Adit, and Okay?
That's a hallucination. This was not in the original text.
But it's factually true. Right?
So, so basically, it's
a real or total notion. If you want to
talk about virtuality and the hallucination hallucination
with respect to what Right?
So, if the model has seen wrong
information in the training data, we really kind of need to understand
where it's coming So
And when LOMs came, we looked into
those things. And we kind of looked into
from fact checking perspective and
there are several things
So, mean, those models are very, very
coherent, very fluent. And it's actually
something very, very dangerous.
Because they are authoritative from wires.
It's not that they hallucinate, it's how
is the fact that they are so, so, you
know, convincing. And then
the public perception that they are
very good in certain cases, this creates an expectation
they are always very good, So
and then, you know, the hidden icon is used for fake
profiles and so on.
And it has been even this information put on the
web targeting LOMs.
Now, how do I address those stats?
Well, many ways. We can detect
whether something was machine generated.
I can tell you a little bit about that.
We can check whether it's coming from. Can
I trust this source? We can do
regulations. We have to be careful with that.
We can promote air literacy.
The same way that we are kind of promoting media literacy
against the fake news. Or we
can make our lives more factual.
It may be here, we are most interested in the
last one. Okay. How can we
make elements more factual? Well,
we can train them. You can kind of clean the
training data Right? Can do
SFG. We can do, you know, GPO. We can
do kind of all kinds of post training, test time
scaling, and so on. We can do
retrieval method generation, That was a big,
big thing. Right, that made it more
factual. Or you can use a larger
model. Right? Why a larger
model is kind of more factual?
Any ideas?
I mean, take one more three. Right? The claim is
that, you know, the it's strengthened on the same 15,000,000,000,000
tokens, you know, the 8,000,000,000 and the 70,000,000,000.
Why 1,000,000,000,000 is less? The
bigger one?
Well, because it has more capacity, it basically,
roughly speaking, over simplifying things.
Those models, they operate in one of two modes.
They are either reciting
their party mode that you have seen in training
or they are making things up. And the
bigger model can remember more, so it has to go into
second mode less often. Okay. That's
super oversimplification.
But And you can do fact
checking. Or you can do a certain quantification.
Okay? Maybe I can tell you a little bit about
uncertainty quantification. Actually, this audience
knows a lot. They have, like, several posters around.
But maybe, Kent, if I can make a little
bit of an advert advertisement for a tool that we
have, Ellen Polleygraph. Which
is something that can tell you
Right? So, the idea is that to understand
whether the model is
certain in what it generates, right,
and what is kind of properly
calibrated. And you can
do this at the entire
generation level or you can do it at the level
of individual claims, right, kind of we can
detect. And when you detect this,
in fact, you know, there
are many, many things that you need to pay attention to.
Right? So, one is that
these different kind of uncertainty, certain uncertainty
is coming from some
of the uncertainty is not related to futurity.
Okay? So, this uncertainty
here, when you start enumerating the awards, do we
start with the Grammy or do you start with the
Golden Guap award? Right? There is this
uncertainty. There is another uncertainty about which tsunami
do I use. Is it the word? Is it price?
Right? And that's
automatic fluctuation. There's other kind of uncertainty
that you need to carry over long distances.
Things like, you know, if you say that she's British singer,
maybe you're uncertain the first time. If lately
in the text is you say she is British, you are
going to condition what you have already said,
attend to that, you're going to be less certain.
So, certain kind of assertiveness you need to carry
over long distances. Right? And there
are many, many other things, kind of. You can do resampling,
kind of this a lot of work actually in
this space. And
one thing that we have, we have this library
called element polygraph. That,
I for a second.
And show you Oh, sorry.
Polygraph. Right?
So there are quite a few
things here implemented. And it's very, very
easy you can, like, plug in any language
model and you can just use it. Right?
So here are the models that are currently
implemented.
It's very, very easy kind of you can wrap it around
any
So, so
Okay. Promised to tell you something a little bit
about fact checking. How can you do fact checking?
Here's a very, very simple idea, you know,
from 2023, we
kind of did '22. I mean,
well, you can just give something
that takes the claim, keeps asking questions about
the claim, gets gets answered somewhere, maybe
from the web, maybe from the internal parameters of the
model, maybe from Wikipedia. Right?
Negative reasons over what happened so far
and then decides whether this contradiction,
where I have enough information. These days, you can
do this kind of with agents. We can call
it back back the agents. That's kind of a simple way to do
it. Another way is I
can say, well, you know, I take the claim,
maybe they composed into different steps that they need
to take. Right? I need to
answer this question. I I need to check
this very simple atomic claim.
And you can just execute a program
that calls a
checking job by just running the program.
Actually, we did this with codex.
Before one of the predecessors of Changshippingiti.
You can do these kinds of things. But
that's about fact checking.
That's before the LOMs came into existence.
Okay? What happened when when LOMs
came? You have a different problem.
We have been doing in factuality, where we
have been checking a claim we have been checking an article
where it's fake news or we have been checking
where I can trust the source,
like that. But we never
reasoned about the problem in a different way. Here's a
text find me everything that
is wrong, fix it.
That's different. Need to take different steps.
Okay? So, you need to kind of first do
decomposing to claims. You need to decontextualize
those claims. You need to decide which of those are check
worthy, which are not. Okay? They
need to get evidence. You need to see whether this evidence
supports or not. And
then you need to decide whether each one is true
or not. Then you need to decide how you fix it. How do
you fix it? Well, maybe I remove
it because it's not fixable or maybe I change one word.
Or maybe I could verify the claim but not
the year Then maybe I can, you know, kind
of dropped some part of the claim.
Right? Then you need to put it together and
maybe kind of present to the user
this is what happened. Right?
Kinda that's my fix. And actually,
we have been working on a system like this kind of we
created a dataset for this that took us maybe,
like, ten months to to
build. And, based on that, we have developed
open fact check It's actually a
quite
big effort. Right? That allows
you it's a system that allows you to
do several things. Right?
Actually, let me let me show
you this.
So it
allows you I'll put here a claim and then I'll
explain. So, if I put something like
I want Musk both
Twitter, in 1985.
And three names. It's
x. I think
that was
a very
smart move. Okay. Let's
see what's gonna happen. Right?
But this system actually allows me to evaluate
certain text allows
me to evaluate an LOM, to evaluate
a fact checker, but also to build
a fact checking system on the fly. Because
here, I have taken different
components. I have a claim processor,
that comes from fact two
have claim retriever again, from
FACT two, but I have our own reasoner, which
is like a fact check GPT, which is kind
of our system. And you can kind of plug and play
and it's really kind of
open source. You can go and do whatever you want.
And he tells me that okay,
happened? First, they can post
into claims. And realized
that this is an opinion.
Therefore, I don't need to fact check that.
Right? Then, you know, here you have
self contained claims. It told
me that's wrong. Gives me the evidence.
Gives me the question that it asked on the
web, explains me the reason.
The reasoning. Right? It's actually and even gives
me a correction Right?
So, and the other claim is true.
Okay, so maybe
I can show you something else. Element Detective.
So, you might want actually to detect
whether something was machine written or not.
And element detected is another
open source
kit where I can, you know, we can just go and
plug it. I will try
it yourself. I can
do
I can take some text
Let me take some text.
And what is
interesting here and something actually important
to realize is that it
you don't should not have just categories human
written, machine generated. You should have things
are in between So
maybe even kind of for the purpose of conference
like this, it might be acceptable to use
tools to polish your text. So, you need to know
whether this was written by a human
written by a machine or written by a human but polished
by a machine. It's this different from entirely
generated. Because you don't want machine
to generate your full article, but it's okay
to polish your English because your English is not so good.
So, let's see.
If I put this here, it tells me this is human
written. Okay? Let me now
go to Jase.
And I can say, I don't know, can
you polish
this text a bit?
Okay. By the way, when we kind of
built, the LOM detective, there was
no trace. Okay. There was kind of not this
version of JS and it was never trained on that. It was
trained on other things. Okay. So,
let me take this text.
So
Let me see.
Okay.
Tells me that it's human written but machine polished. Right?
And this kind of an intermediate category
important to realize. Right?
Okay. So,
I mean, maybe kind of another point that I
want to make here is that I mean,
the is the connection between machine generated
and factuality? Right? We have
done some some some thing actually, this is probably
now published, but anyway.
So we have been working into we
took old data sets
for fake news detection
and and kind of we
have been playing with with kind of new generation synthetic
data basically we found
two biases. That if you
train here's what happens. If I train
model, tell me whether something is fake news
or not, on the pre
Gen AI era from the classic
fake news data sets. Okay? And I
applied to different
text. I tried on human
real, human fake machine real
machine, you know, factual, machine non
factual, I find two biases. Number one,
it thinks that machine generated
kind of real news are fake. And
things that human written fake news are real.
Now, let's put about the first thing.
To think that the machine generated
news is fake was a good thing in
the old times before Gen AI. Because if
it's machine generated, it's like to be something
to be fishy there because the reviews were never
written by humans.
But now, you need to think what is going on. Right? Because,
like, in the past, the vast
majority of the real news was human written
Now, you have a mixed situation. In the future,
it can be that most of the real news are
human written, and the detector
that tells you that anything that is kind of machine
written is kind of likely
fake that's a not good detector anymore.
And, if you have a kind of like design strategy
is how it should be. Training detectors
right, to really focus on factuality, not on what
the origin is in the different scenarios.
Maybe to finish here, right,
maybe my last thought is that
I don't think that this is going to be one element
to rule demo. This was actually
the original view This is what people
thought. There's going to be one supersystem.
In fact, now we we have systems,
not really models. But
I want to tell you about
something that we have in Mohammed Meset
University of Artificial Intelligence. We have
an entire Institute on Foundation Models
and we have branches in Abu Dhabi,
in Paris, in Silicon Valley,
And, we don't believe
in one model for everything. Okay?
And, this is kind of just like to give
you some illustration. Right? I mean, what kind
of told you a little bit about this k two,
it's a 70,000,000,000 model for Arabic
data thinking model that's a separate
one. This kind of j's which is
specialized in Arabic.
This kind of specialized on dialect, Egyptian
dialect. This specialized on
on, Moroccan dialect.
This is Kazah. This is
Hindi. Then we have models
for biology. Those are specialized on
biological sequences. That's great for precision
medicine. For,
designing artificial digital organisms,
There are world models Right? So
so really,
it's not just one model that can have
everything
And we
we need
fully open
source and transparent open models,
not just open but also open weight,
open data, We want language
specific models and in general specialized
models And we want safe
models and you want factual
models. Thank you
very much.
Thank you so much. We have
time for one or two questions. Anybody
has a question,
There was one question actually through the chat.
So I'm gonna ask that one,
for now while other people think.
And, it was why not just a specialized
tokenizer? Per language, why a full
model per language? Because
were talking earlier about the need for
Oh, no. Tokenization being
different per language. And I guess that's
how I understand the question Yeah. Of speaking. Yeah. Okay.
So I mean, like, the thing is that I
focused on
explaining one problem only, that's tokenization.
But when you go to another language, there are
many, many things. So,
there are things about how do
you make it safe what is safe
in one culture, differs from what is
safe in other culture? I have also kind of already
made the point. There can be different
views on historical events or you
talk about different
groups of people, and so on
and so forth. Then
kinds of capabilities that you need to handle
are different. In certain languages, you
might want to have code switching.
So it's
it's it's and then there's
another thing. But
but it's more than that. I gave you the case of Arabic,
But even, let's say, you can take
English Okay? If I if
I have a model let's say,
JS, right, it's a model that is for Arabic,
but it has twice as much English than Arabic.
Why do you want English in the model?
In an Arabic model? Well, for one, there
is okay. For many reasons. One of
them is that, well, our original reason
was we didn't have enough training data
and you didn't have enough tokens for parameter.
Then it was not that that problem, but
are other capabilities that you might want to teach
in English, how to do math and other things. You
don't need to teach it in Arabic. But
there are other things. You want
it to be able to translate.
So, that's why you want English. But now the question is
what's English? Okay?
If I take English from local news agencies,
it's gonna be a different kind of English. It might have different
view of the world, different knowledge,
over about companies, places,
entities, relationship between players, regional
and globally. So,
it's you need different models.
It actually kind of have different viewpoints.
And ones that are reflecting the specific
area where you want to deploy it.
So it's not just about the organization.
It's about the knowledge
Great. Thank you.
There's one question here from the audience as
well. One last question. Perfect. Thank you.
Hi. I have two questions.
One is that, beside,
even in two countries which speak Arabic,
they might have different definitions for
different concepts, like a conservative politician
is very different in Arabic
country, or conservative political
parties. Conceive differently in different
countries if you bother to the same language.
How do you deal with such situations
And then beside that,
there are also different vape people
interact, in their own language, like
it's not like, a chat is probably not always
the the main way of interactions.
Maybe some information will be lost.
In in the written form? And
this third question is, how do you do
knowledge transfer, like you
partially answered that with, like, putting
some data from a different
language inside the training data.
But we have, like, all these different models
with different, language,
and you can't really
cover some there are some information
not available in some language definitely.
So how do you take care of this knowledge transfer?
Yeah. I mean, those are all great questions. So
the first one I, Kef,
you know, kind of
partially addressed. So
we the
the the way that
we have been working into different strategies
of of what language models are doing, right?
Because we have worked a lot on safety.
Right? And here, like, in fact, in our university
also have a startup that is
working in this area. We have more closely working
with them. And they have
big clients like OpenAI and, you know,
Entropic and so on. Kind of who really
kind of came walking into what the best strategies
sometimes we can even work even working with them
on developing our safety mechanisms.
So it's
it's a very interesting thing because there's a balance
that you need to strike between
utility and safety If initially, kind of, the model was
very safe but was not that useful because kind
of it denies too much. Know,
if it says, I don't discuss religion, I don't
discuss politics, that's very easy. To do, but
then it's not useful. Right? So, if I ask you
how do I fast during Ramadan, what is wrong with
answering this question? There's nothing wrong, right?
So, if you should not be over denying.
Right? So so,
the way that you do it
you know, there are things where you have
to be harsh. I have shown kind of in the
study of how different models are reacting to the don't
tell serve. There are things here you don't want to have any
tolerance. Because it's kind of bad. But
there are other cases
where it's better actually to have
to be a good politician. Right, kind
of to try to this is what politicians
do. Right? Kind of they they are deflecting
things, and they are kind of trying
to you know, to smooth
it and to kind of, you know, acknowledge this also
different viewpoint. And, so one thing
that I want to stress is that when we are building these
models, we have never put
any efforts, zero, to
to kind of align with one specific
agenda or political viewpoint or whatever
kind of we have trying the model to be safe
you know, in general terms, kind of maybe in regional
specific terms and whatever, but not kind of to
reflect one specific viewpoint. I think that's
important. Right? So,
and what else? I mean, another
thing is kind of like really putting data
from the region, from the
and then we had a lot of
manual evaluation working
also internally, but also externally.
One thing that I can tell you that
any important decision about the
model regardless of all those benchmarks
and so on, have made based on
manual analysis, manual evaluation.
Is no substitute for that. And kind of each time is
new things, right, that we or
we invent or kind of we hire companies
to invent for us. That's kind of
a repetitive process. And
when you detect that something is not right,
kind of work on this. You saw it but not to solve
this specific case but kind of solve it in a more
generic way.
Thank you so much. I think we're
well over time already and, you all
keen to get the coffee and the snacks from the coffee
break that's happening right now. So
let's, thank our speaker once again. Thank you
so much for being here.
So we now have a coffee break. And
at 03:30, we will have our
next invited talk.
Alright. Welcome back everybody.
I hope you enjoyed the coffee and the
cake and the burger.
We come to the last invited
talk of today before we will finish
with a panel discussion and
a, of course, thank you
and award ceremony at the very end.
But, now it is my great
pleasure to introduce our next
invited speaker, Se Won. Se Won
Min, is an assistant professor
at UC Berkeley. A research
scientist at the Allen Institute for AI.
Her research lies in the intersection
of natural language processing and machine learning.
Of course, nowadays with a focus on large language
models. She studies the science
of LLMs and develops new models
and training methods for better performance,
flexibility, and adaptability. Such as
retrieval based LMS, mixture of experts,
modular systems. She
also studies LLM for information seeking, factuality,
privacy, and mathematical reasoning.
Prior, she has earned her PhD from
the University of Washington and
had various research roles at Meta, Google,
and Salesforce. But importantly,
today, she will talk about mixture of experts
and whether they are modular, why that
matters, and how to fix it. Thank you.
Thank you for the introduction. Hello,
everyone. Thank you. For being here, and
I'm really excited to be here and talk
about mixed or tax approach and for whether
they are modular just
like oh, sorry.
Yeah. So today, I'm excited to
be here and talk about mixed effects.
Fax Bridge. Are they modular just
like their name suggests? Why it matters?
And how to fix it. And this work
is done jointly with Ryan Huang, who
is my PhD student at UC Berkeley,
as well as Akshita, who is
our collaborator at AI2. So
Cool. So just talk us about mixer facts
first. So let me start with a brief
overview just to get everyone on the same
page. So So So this
is a standard dense model that is not
on MOE As you can see, it has
a few small layers like multi attention,
and then on FFN. And this
FFN usually contains the majority
of model parameters. Now
with an MOE, you typically
you replace the single effepn with
many smaller networks called
experts. For example, instead of
one FFN, you can have one twenty
eight expert or even more.
And then the key idea is that we don't use
all of them at once. We only
activate a small subset of them.
So just to give how it works,
For simplicity, this is the small
illustration where we assume we have
10 total experts that's n, and two
active experts that's k. Now
each token makes its own decision
on which tool out of 10
experts to activate.
So for instance, the first token,
though, can choose to activate each
two and e six. The next token
cell can choose to activate e one and
e four. Next token chooses
e five and e eight, and
so on until the end. So each token
make their own decision on what to activate.
And the key idea is that in terms of
efficiency and compute,
it is much closer to the smaller
model that only have two FFNs.
While still benefiting from a larger
set of parameters. It's much
better in terms of capability.
And so these MOUs are
widely proven to be very effective.
Building much better performance with the same amount
of data and compute. So
these are the graph from the OumuI paper. It's
an open source MOE that we presented
at ICLAR last year, and
we can see it's outperforming dense
model over many different metrics. And
this trend has been very consistent
over the years in the literature.
And today, nearly
all foreign tier models are MOS.
This is a summary table of some representative
models in the recent few years
starting from DeepSick MOE, DeepSick
v three, and more recently, Nemotron
and GLM five. I only listed a
few of them.
It doesn't include DeepSpeech before
because it came up very recently, and I made a
test before that. But, obviously, before
DeepSpeech v four is also a
MOE. So there are many
numbers here. I'm not going to cover all the
details, but you you read it, you can see
the growing trend, which is they're
becoming larger and
sparser and also finer grained.
For instance, all the deep sea models
have about 40,000,000,000
active and 7,000,000,000 total parameters.
GLM is the same. So a lot of models
have the similar structure. So this is
great. This is exciting.
But it also means these models are
extremely memory intensive.
Because in terms of compute, they behave
more like a smaller model, but
they still need to load all the param
all the total parameters into the memory
even if they're not activated. So
that means as an individual like
you and me, it's very hard to
use it locally. You can use
API thanks to some serving companies
with massive infrastructure
in distributed serving. But if you want
to run it locally, it's very difficult.
Fine tuning is a bit more difficult since inference
is already difficult. So that means using them
is very difficult unless you have large
scale infrastructure.
Okay. So that's kind of the idea
for MOE. Now in today's
talk, I'm gonna ask the central question.
Are MOUs modular?
And that means they're going to ask these two
sub questions.
Do experts in MOAs specialize
in distinct capabilities or domains.
Which is kind of what we expect because the names
are experts. We want experts
so we specialize in their
capabilities or domains.
And if that is true, then that
means it should be possible to
do selective composition
Meaning, if you care about a specific downstream
task, you should be able to select a subset
of them and compose them and
be able to use it. So is that true?
So if that is possible, the dream scenario
is as follows. So let's
say this is your entire model. It has one twenty
eight expert. And then
you want to use it for a math task.
Then instead of loading all apps perch,
you wanna be able to select
only a subset of experts related to
math and use that with very
little performance drop. And
then if you want to use it for a different task
like biomedical, want to select
all different set of experts
related to biomedical, and
use that. And same if you have another
domain like policy, then you want
to choose a subset of them. It should be able
to maintain performance. That's kind of
the idea. Not only did
it's conceptually very natural and
desirable and very clean, but
if this is possible, it has significant
practical implementation. Because as I
said earlier, loading all experts
and MOUs are very
memory intensive, as your
MOE gets bigger and sparser. In
fact, there are many papers studied this, including
papers presented in I and also
papers that have been
archived in recent few years. So this
is a big problem. And people
tackle this in different views. Some people
wanna restrict the total number
of parameters. Some papers
proposed to modify the infrastructure
but in this talk, we are making a complementary
view, which is the MOA has
should be modular so that we can do selective
use of expert. Okay.
So that's the question we're gonna ask.
So we should know look at
each each of the sub questions. So let's first look
at whether experts specialize.
So, there are many ways to analyze
that. But what we did is we look
at expert activated patterns
of the spender and voice. We made
it a vector and then we took k
mesh cloth strings. So we have clusters. And then we
look at how each cluster looks like. And
we got some help from Cloud Code to help this
analysis. And this is how the
clusters look like. And
if you would take a look, I hope everyone can read
it. But if you take a look, you can see
they are specializing, but at a
lexical level or some sort of surface
level. So there is a cluster
about be verb, There's a
cluster about active verb. Cluster
about preposition,
cluster about conditional phrases,
so these are how they specialize. And if you
look at one of them, this is conditional
clauses. So the corresponding tokens
are tokens like,
but, so, when, that, and so
on. So this is
good, but they're specializing at a
slightly different way as we expected because this
is not domain level or semantic level.
K. So what does it
mean in terms of selective expertise?
Meaning, for a specific downstream
domain, we want to select a sub set of
relevant experts and be able to use them.
So we try to evaluate
that aspect. So we look
at MMLU and MMLU Pro because each
of these benchmark include
a few sub sub task. I think in total,
like, 30 sub task, for
distinct domains, like math, physics,
psychology, and so on. So we
can consider each subtask as,
specific domain and then do selective data
used for each. And these
bars represent the full model that has one
twenty eight apps per And now let's
see what happens if you choose a foxlet
So this is what happens if you cut it to
half. And already,
there is some substantial drop.
Now when we drop it to 32,
drop is more significant. And
then when we drop it to sixteen and eight,
these are basically same as random
guessing performance. And then just to
collaborate the result, we can also compare
with a dense model. And, typically,
MOE should be much better than this.
But when we choose a subset, they are
all worse than this. So this means
oh, selective expert users not really working
with vendor MOS.
Okay. But this is a model, pre
trained for one thirty billion tokens. So what
about when we train longer? Let's say
1,000,000,000,000 tokens. So
absolute numbers are higher as we expect When
we cut it to half,
quite substantial drop.
Further than that is more significant
drop until when we cut into eight. So
maybe the way we chose our
subserve expert was wrong. So
we tried many different selection method,
including the method that is called ECP.
It's one of the state of the art expert
pruning method that we took from recent
papers it was mostly the same.
They didn't make big difference.
Okay. So what do we learn here? There
are some takeaways. First,
even though standard MOAs have modular
architecture they not functionally
modular. And this makes
MOS a little difficult to use
or fine tune in practice unless you have
massive multi node
serving infrastructure. And this is increasingly
true as MOS gets
larger and sparser.
And we want to make a claim that
we should continue to train
on that is very large in spires because
why not? This is compute
efficient and performant. But we
should train an MOE with modularity
as a first step class
citizen because right now, standard MOEs
do not meet that criteria.
Okay. So that's the topic that
the rest of the talk will cover. To train
an MOE with modularity.
K. So let's consider all the options
and first of all, just to clarify, we
are not the first one to ask this
question. There has been pretty good literature
that covers the same question. And one
of the common approach many papers
took is to assign domain labels
for the data and expert in induced learning.
So typical process looks like this.
We have pretraining data. This is general
web data, multitrillion token.
Then we partition them based on semantic
domains like biomedical, math, and so on.
And then we kind of do mapping
between this data and app to
induce that, okay. This expert should
specialize in this domain. Like, expert
one should be specializing in biomedical,
Expert two is a math expert, and
so on. And there are many
papers on that. I just added two of them.
One of them is actually my own work.
So this is this has nice properties
for different reasons. But
in this talk, I'm going to argue these are actually
not optimal. One reason
is that domain labels are inherently
ambiguous. And are difficult to
obtain, especially when it comes to multitrillion
corpora. And their message also difficult
to generalize to unscentedomics.
Personally, what I find even more
important is
this is imposing human prior and
the lesson we learned from deep learning? That means
more human prior we imposed, it's worse.
So hopefully, we want the model
to be more to learn without imposing
human prior. We want it to sort
of, like, natively emerge in a
self supervised way without needing to
give human prior. So that's
what we wanna do. So the question is,
how can we do that? Can we induce modularity
to emerge without human prior?
And we wanna do that by changing the learning of
the So So how do we do that?
Okay. So we made a few key
assumptions. One is
tokens coming from the same domain
should activate a similar subset of
experts so that it encourages
localizes expertise. So in
that way, experts can naturally
emerge expertise in a semantic level.
But then how do we determine
which tokens are coming from the same domain? So
we made another assumption.
Which is if tokens are coming from the same document,
they're likely to share the domain.
And if you kind of combine this, we can
make a proposal which is let's encourage
token from the same document to activate a
shared pool of experts. So that they are more
localized in terms of expert
So that's kind of the key idea. So
how do we exactly do that? We
call our model mode MOE. So
this is mode MOE's objective.
So, okay, we see the same figure we
saw earlier. This is 10
total experts, and we are going to activate two
experts. So each token chooses
two out of 10. That's regular MUE.
Now what we are going to do
is we wanna restrict activation
a subset of them per document.
So per document, we identify a
pool of the expert.
Here, d is four. So we choose
these four experts based on which
experts are likely to be preferred by tokens
coming from this particular document.
Once we identify this pool, then
we restrict activation of tokens
from this document to be restricted to
this set. So
each token chooses two out of four.
Importantly, each token still makes an
independent decision. They can act
experts, but they are restricted to
this smaller So
And, importantly, this pool changes
across different documents. So for instance,
in pretraining, it is very common to
concatenate multiple documents
to form a single sequence. So even within a
single sequence, there are we have multiple documents. So we have multiple documents to form a single sequence. So even within a single sequence, there are multiple documents.
You have a new document here, it's
in codomain, then you will have its
own pool of four x perch, and then
each token from this document
will choose two out of these four experts.
So that's kind of how it works.
So Yeah. This
is the same idea, but we just use
cloud code to give us a prettier
illustration. But the idea is exactly
the same. On the left, we have standard
MOAs that choose two out of
10. No matter if tokens are coming
from same document or not. And
then on the right, we have Mode m way, which
is our model. It first chooses a pool of
four, and then each token chooses
two out of four. Is that clear?
Cool. So this is our method. Hopefully,
I think this is conceptually simple.
That was what we wanted. This is conceptually simple.
However, just like any other pretraining projects
or architecture projects,
actually making it work was very
challenging. Sometimes the training
was unstable. Sometimes we had lost
spikes. So in to
make it actually work, we had to come up with a lot of
small twist. To
make it work. They're very, very small.
So I don't think I should even say
all of this in this talk. But they were very critical
to make you work. So in this talk, I'll
talk about only one of them. Which is
load balancing. So if you're
familiar with MOEs, you'll probably know how
important load balancing is.
And, typically, it works as follows.
So let's say this is your batch.
Your batch contain four documents.
Then each document will have their own
activation statistics.
Something like this, across 10 different experts. Some
of them will be used more. Some of them will
less. But then
we when we train this model,
we aggregate the statistics
and make sure that all experts are used
in a somewhat uniform way so that
the expert use is balanced.
And typically, you do this by adding
an auxiliary loss. This is very
important. And so on the left,
is what happens if you don't do load balancing.
So you can see that essentially,
what that means is only two experts
are being ever used All the other
experts are completely dead. So that means
your performance will be stopped
Now after you look at load balancing,
which is on the right, then
all experts are being used roughly
uniformly. Okay. So this load
balancing is very important. But
how does it work in our model?
So conceptually, it is a little
weird. Because our objective is somewhat
like, reverse of load balancing because
we want use of experts to
be restricted. Not uniform.
However, we still can use load balancing
because the restriction is
per document. Load balancing is per batch.
So we can still use it. So this one
looks like this. Each document have its
activation statistics. Each document
will be restricted to four experts. But
each document have their own pool. So
in aggregation, we can still do load balance.
Okay. So we tried that,
and it kinda works. Like, it
gave a good performance. But when we look at
the gradient norm across training, it looks
like this. So gradient normally
has to be zero and very smooth.
We see there are some spikes. So
this is not good. This means training is
not as stable as we hoped. We have
to fix this. So
we try to understand and look closer
to the code base be because we
are using the one of the existing
MOE training code bases.
And we found that
actually, that code base was using
micro batch load balancing.
And by the way, this is very common
in most of the MOE training. Most
of them use micro batch level load
balancing. What that means is
so the global batch is actually
set of microbatches based on
local GPU. And then instead of
load balancing over global batch,
they do micro batch level
load balancing for many different reasons. This
makes implementation easier. This means
training efficiency is slightly better. So
they did And that's
fine for spender mo e. But
in our case, that's not really good.
Because maybe micro batch only have
two documents, and each document
only activates four experts.
So enforcing load balancing
with this very small set of
documents makes training a little
unstable and makes load balancing very
difficult. So So we find
that out and then we fixed it.
Simply by just implementing
global level of balancing. So it was a little
demanding work because that means each GPU
has to we should do, like, cross GPU
communication. We should implement
this. You know? Efficient way and so
on, but we did that because
we thought it was improving for our objective.
And then, low spikes were gone. Okay.
That low spike. The gradient norm spikes were gone.
After adding global load balance,
we end up with the red bar,
which is more steep.
So, yeah, that was one of our tricks that
we made. We had to make other small
tweaks to make this work. But we are able to make
training stable in the end.
Okay. So that was our method. Now, I'll
move on to experiment. I'll not
go over all the details of training because they will
be a little boring, but just to put
a few important information, we
pre train from scratch using
our new object We train
our main model for 1,000,000,000,000 tokens
but we also did most of the oblations
on one thirty billion So
We try one b active 14 b
total parameters in terms of number of
experts. That's eight active, one twenty eight
total experts. Our model is
obviously much smaller than deep sea models. But
in terms of number of expert and
how fine grain it is, it is actually
comparable to those frontier models.
We use the same training data as Omo
e, which is our prior open source MOE
model, one and a half years ago.
One thing I was personally quite proud of
is we made a lots of general
architecture improvement on top of MOE.
To make our baseline as competitive
as possible. So
these are some small tricks
that are kind of like
very small, like prenorm instead
of postnorm, removing 2K
norm, adding shared experts, and so on.
But in the end, we were able to
make our baseline model
better than Omoi model, even though we trained
for 1,000,000,000,000 tokens only while
Omoi was trained for 5,000,000,000,000
tokens. So we were kind of proud
of this because that means we made our baseline
MOE as competitive as possible.
Cool. So that's training.
And just to give a brief overview of
evaluation, so our main goal
is to allow selective expert use that
we looked at earlier So want
to be able to use choose a subset of
experts for each downstream task But
we also wanna make sure our overall performance of
the original model is good because otherwise,
nobody would wanna use it. So
we did both evaluations.
K. Let me first show you
the overall performance, and we mainly compare
with Omo e. Our
tokens. These bars are from Omoi.
This is our standard MOE, which
is our own baseline model. So
as you can see, we are slightly better than OMOE
even though it was trained for a five x
less tokens, which is nice.
And then here is our model, which is Mode
MUE. So it is very close to regular
MOE. So This
is consistent when we train for love
tokens like one thirty billion tokens,
which is five chinchilla. So this is
a dense model. And then this
is regular MOE. So
as expected, regular MOE is
much better than things. And then
finally, this is our model. So our model
is quite close sometimes
even better than regular MOE when we
use as a overall model.
So take away is we are matching regular
MOE in overall performance.
And Now let's look at what happens with selective
data use Meaning, we will
choose our subset of relevant experts for
every domain and see how much performance drop.
So this is a graph we saw
earlier already on how regular MOE
works in this case. For MMLU
and MMLU pros. So across
all benchmarks and settings, the regular
MOE didn't really support selective
expertise. Because performance drop was too
significant. Now, here's
how our model works. This
is a full model with one twenty eight experts.
As we saw earlier, the full model performance
is very close to regular MOE.
This is when we cut to half. And as you
can see, the performance drop is
near zero. Sometimes even better.
So there's very little drop when we cut it
to half. And we cut it to
a 32, there is little bit of
drop, but still very marginal compared
to regular AMU. When we drop
it to 16, again,
pretty small drop.
When we cut to eight, which is an extreme case
because that means we are activating
all eight experts, then there is a
little bit more significant drop. But
but still much better than the regular MOE.
In fact, you can see our model
according to 16 x and
is already better than regular MUE that
cut to half. And
And just to give a collaboration, this
is a dense model performance, so all
of our models no matter the
dispersal ratio is, is better than this.
So, yeah, these are some takeaways. So
first, more than we support functional
modularity because we changed the training
objective, and enabled using subset
of expert for downstream task which
is great because that means
don't have a memory problem anymore for serving
and fine tuning. Now individuals like
and me can, even if you just
have one GPU or one node, we
can use it for
downstream task by choosing a subset of apps
per turn. And then I didn't
show in this talk, but in the paper,
we found this is consistent across zero
shot inference in and fine tuning. So
you can use it for even fine tuning.
On just one GPU. And then also,
we find it consistent across different selection
methods. You can use pretty
simple chip basic selection
method or state of the art printing method, and the
train is very consistent.
So that's good. We also look at how
experts specialize because that was one of the thing
we were curious about. So we saw earlier
that standard MOE specialized
but at a lexical level. Kind of
at a surface level rather than semantic
level. So we saw clusters are something
like active verb,
prepositions, and so on. We did
our exactly same analysis with
our Mode MOE. And found that
they specialize semantic levels.
And that was kinda nice because we
never explicitly encouraged that.
So this semantic specialization
kinda emerged natural. So if you
look at some of the clusters, some
of them are about health and
medical, of them are about tech, how
to, and system admin.
Of them are about food and cooking.
Some of them are about sports
and athletics. And so on. So
the semantic semantics specialization
kind of naturally merge. And
And there is another thing I wanna mention, which
is from the system perspective, this is
actually a really exciting opportunity
because this allows much faster
serving even when we don't do
selective expert use.
Of the reasons is in regular MOE,
if you cannot load all the experts in memory,
you have to do a lot of switching,
because and every neighboring tool can use
different sets of experts. So that makes serving
really slow.
In, you don't have to do that because it
neighboring tokens stick with one set of experts.
With throughout the sequence. So even
with all limited memory setup, you don't
have to do a lot of switching, and that can make serving
very efficient. So that's
kind of the something we didn't
look deep into about can create a very
exciting opportunity.
Cool. So that's kind of it. I
will wrap up with a few
takeaways. So in the beginning
of the talk, I mentioned that MOS are
scaling larger and spars for
reasons that makes training
efficiency much better. It makes
capabilities to be better, which is great.
But most are being used as an
API service for individuals like us.
Because to serve this MOS, you
need massive multinode infrastructure.
So you want to run it locally,
it's hard to use. And even
harder to find tune. So we claim
that we want to make use of modularity
in MOAs to solve this
problem. Standard MOAs do not support this. We so
we train our own model
with a modified training
objective. With modularity as a
first class citizen. So when
our end our end goal is something like
this, when we have an MOE with one twenty eight expert,
want to be able to choose a subset of relevant experts
for every downstream task. So
what we found is it is possible
to train this with improved efficiency
and performance by the selective expert
use We can achieve this without any
human prior so that this emerged naturally.
No sacrifice and overperforms. So
the performance is still as good as regular
movie. And we'll also look at the
specialization happens kind of
naturally. Even though we don't enforce it.
And they're specializing in terms of semantics,
not just lexicon.
I think there are many exciting future
directions that we didn't fully explore
in this one piece of work. Instance,
we wanna integrate it into
larger and sparser and finer
grain and more ish because the impact will be even larger.
We want to make serving much better
as I motivated just last flight.
And finally, we think this modularity
has lots of potential beyond selective
expertise. For instance, it is possible
to support this to
enable modular MOE training,
not just modular MOE use. So
I think there are more exciting work to be done,
and would be happy to chat more about it.
Yeah. That's it. Thank you for listening, and I'm happy
to take questions.
Thank you so much. Okay. We have one question
right here. Unfortunately, we will only have
time for one question. So good for you
for being quick. Thank you very much.
I had the same idea, but,
not so long ago. I had a
question, like, is it possible to post train
normal regular MAE to become this?
Or it's impossible in principle?
That's a very great question. So if I'm understanding
question correctly, is it possible to take the
regular MOE pre trained with a
regular objective and maybe do mid training
or control training to make it
Yeah. We did small operations where
we compare the model
trained from scratch, and then the model
which we took a standard model and then
took mid training with this objective. We've
find that training from scratch is
much better, which maybe not surprising, but
me training actually also induce
some of discomfort. So we did very little
mid training, so that wasn't, like, very good.
But I think it's possible that if you do
very long mid training with this new object
it is possible to introduce modularity.
Thank you.
Alright. Let's thank our speaker once again. Thank you
so much, Seylan.
And the reason why we don't have
time for more question is that we have an
exciting panel coming up. So, if
the panel panelist and panel
moderator could take the stage. I guess you
take it from there. Jennifer, my co organizer will
be the moderator. Thank you. And
we have a hard cut at five, so let's go.
Alright. Yeah. If all of the panelists can come
up and take a seat, then we can
get started.
If you wanted, that'd be very sad.
Yeah. Yeah. Alright. And
did we
I know he's literally just here all
No. I
know. Okay.
Alright. We'll get started.
Alright, everybody. So we're gonna
get started. Prezlaff just had to
to step out, so he will be back in a moment, but
I'm gonna start with everyone's intros.
Because as Arno mentioned, we are quite short
on time because we need to make sure that we
fully wrap up by five. So I wanna leave as much
time as possible for all of
our great panelists to answer our questions.
So I'm gonna start going down
the line with some just brief introductions so
everybody understands everybody's context.
So first, we've got Martha,
Garnello, and she currently
leads a research team at Fundamental
as a chief scientist officer.
Where she's focused on building foundation
models for tabular data. And
before this, she spent over seven years
as a researcher at DeepMind.
Next, we have Sammy Benjio, who
is currently the senior director
of ML research at Apple. And
his research focuses on many aspects
of machine learning, including deep
architectures, representation learning, vision,
and language processing, as well as
reasoning. Before this, he was
a distinguished scientist at Google Research,
heading part of the Google Brain team.
And at IDIAP where
he helped co write Torch.
Then we have Si Woon Min, who just
gave us our last great talk,
and she is an assistant professor
at EECS at UC Berkeley.
And she's also affiliated, with
Berkeley AI Research as part of that work.
And a research scientist at the Allen Institute
for AI. And her research, as
we just learned a lot about, is that the
intersection of NLP and ML,
with a focus on LLMs.
And before this, she's held research roles
at Meta AI, Google, and Salesforce.
And Prezlov will be back shortly,
so I'm gonna give a quick quick intro.
There we go. See? Coming to the stage
right now. So he is a
professor and department
chair of NLP at the
Mohammed bin Zayed University of AI
and and his research includes
developing open source LLMs,
including an Arabic centered LLM,
a Hindi model, and a Kazakh model.
Sorry for butchering those names.
And before this, he was a principal
scientist at Qatar
Computing Research Institute. So really
excited to have the panelists, and we're just gonna dive into
a question that I'd love to hear an answer,
from each of you on. So we've
heard a lot about today about different
areas and problems on which
LLMs still need to improve.
So we wanna start the discussion by hearing from
each of you what you
can't believe isn't better. So So what's
the most surprising way in which LLMs
still need to improve?
Well, so
me, the the thing that kinda surprised me
is, how little we have advanced
on factuality. So
looks and know,
even even with testing scaling, even with,
all the efforts, even with track,
the models to
generate output, it's not factual. That's the thing.
And and that has been clear
from the time the charge g p t first came
A lot of effort has been done. A lot of
advancements have been done. Surprisingly, it's
not solved. And if you think about it, so,
in terms of search engines, for example. Right?
So, never
hit super much complaints about, in there,
fake news about Google. Right? Because
they have figured out what is high
information, why we cannot figure out
now produce high quality
output you know, out of our lives.
I I guess we can go in order.
Yeah. So I guess I'm personally most
excited about data and architectural foundation
models. So I'm more interested
in, like, what they seems to
be not good at yet. Like, how to be more data
efficient, how to be more
computer efficient, memory efficient, and so
on. But also I really agree that factuality
seems to be surprise one of the surprising things
that models are surprisingly not good
at. Especially, how long
given how long we've been talking about it. Like,
how much we talk about hallucination, being
able to cite, being able to provide
provenance so that users can
verify This seems like one
of those that we've been talking for many years
and still haven't really
fixed, and how to also even
incorporate, new knowledge that is
emerging, how to continuously learn over
time and so
on. So I have a few,
let me maybe the first one is a
recent realization that
we had in our team that
as as models get very good
at generating stuff,
particular, for instance, they are very good at generating
code. You probably most
of you use a subform of,
cloud code on competitors.
You kind of think that they actually
understand code,
but if you
and the experiment that we tried which was very
surprising was to give
them code or pseudo code
to simplify as a as
input. And ask them to follow
the pseudocode to tell us what will be the answer.
And and they were not able to
do so. So
it's kind of a failure that I'm not sure
I totally understand, but it's
it's, it surprised me.
The other thing that, I don't understand
why it's still not solved is the fact that,
we still need prompt engineers. In
a way, finding the
right prompt for the right question
seems still to be hard.
Changing a few small bits of your prompt
and gets, false
or true answer is still
surprising today with the large models we
have.
So my answer is not gonna be a big surprise given
my talk this morning. But what
I find surprising is maybe it's not
this surprising, but how
LLMs are really good at reasoning in the
language space as their name indicates,
and they can do it in code better or
worse, but they can do it for other types
of text. But they're really bad with numbers.
And this is also a bit what I covered about when it comes
to actually sitting down and
doing number crunching, they're really bad. And they pretend
they're good because that's what they're also good at. At telling you
that they're doing this confidently and well. Right?
And there's this huge discrepancy between
the round anything that any
objective or anything that you can express
in words any reasoning trace, anything
that you can actually capture in words,
LLMs at least seem to be getting a
stab at it. If it's something numerical,
you're completely on your own for now. And I
think that this discrepancy for me, the more I've interacted with
with it, was the more jarring.
Nice. Thank you all so much for sharing.
Because, right, we all see limitations in different
ways, and so it's helpful for us to all discuss
them part of the motivation behind this workshop. So So
another thing I'm curious about and has been a popular
topic throughout the conference is there's been
a lot of progress around reasoning, such
a chain of thought, tool use,
test time compute, etcetera.
So do you think current improvements
reflect real reasoning ability
or better scaffolding around a still
limited core model?
Dad, go for it. So I personally
think that, mean, at least in
the last one year, most
of the improvement that we have seen has been coming
from two calling,
not so much from reasoning,
and it feels like that the ability
to improve of kind of
the advancement as we have done at least in one
year in two calling to improve the capability
of the systems want to stress
systems.
Has been much bigger than the
cape the improvements in capabilities
of the model the model and
the system. We have done via
reasoning. So,
and in
a way, this might be the way even
forward. You have already
quite reasonable reasonably
strong language models, but they are lacking
And, actually,
the access to external information is one thing
that has helped reduce
the problems related to factuality,
to lack of more recent data, and so on
and so forth. But also things that
you know, have been mentioned here
about numerical things. Why should the
language model do numerical operations? You should
just kind of parse it in something that can be
passed to an external
calculator. Or to something that can generate
little Python code. And in fact, deep research now is
looking into that.
I for me, and I'm not an ex expert
in reasoning for LLMs at all, but,
it does feel to me like
even the work around the harness is in itself
potentially the way to go towards reasoning. And I remember,
like, in 2016, when people
at DeepMind were looking at how do we do reasoning traces
and we were trying to do it in like latent spaces, which were
just abstract
numbers that meant nothing. And there wasn't a lot of success
around that at the time. I think the
fact that we can now ground it in language, which is something
that this model itself can then work with,
allows to maybe enable this
reasoning that maybe wasn't there before. Right? So I think
even the harness around it can be a step towards
creating
reasoning.
I think, we're making progress in reasoning,
for sure, but it's not an even
progress. There are places where
we make a very good progress and I mean,
again, the the best example is
coding environment. I think in the past few
months, it it's became
very clear that they are useful.
So so do they
reason? I'm not sure. It's hard to
use these terms, but clearly, they are
for very hard tasks,
But this usually happen for a couple of reasons.
One is there's a lot of data
and the second one is it's easy
to verify in some ways
whether they did something right or not. So
training, using, RL or any
other technique becomes much easier.
So we're making progress but
more in a brute force version of
it. Rather than in
a in a clear algorithmic perspective
that could be useful for other fields
where there's not that much data and it's unclear
what's working and what's not.
So in that sense, I don't think we have made
the the progress I would like
hope I would hope to to have made in
reasoning.
Yeah. I I don't think we made
meaningful progress in reasoning. And, of course, I think
the definition,
like how human made reasoning, I don't
think that's not the case. But also,
we don't have to expect AI model to reason
like humans, I think what matters is whether
they can do downstream task for
us. And for that, I think we did
made meaningful progress, but I
also agree with Sammy that
this is true for certain tasks,
especially, I think for a very well defined
task, we do made a lot of
meaningful progress, and maybe end of the year, we will
completely be so like automated,
completely automates some task
if they're well defined and
easily verifiable. However, I think
there are a lot of real world tasks
where it's even hard to define because
it's so open ended, very to
verify, maybe take years to verify. And for
that, I think still have lots
of way to go.
Thanks. It's great to hear the nuance
behind the fact that we have made progress, but
in exactly what ways and what's
the right direction to actually move forward.
So building off of that,
one question is, you know,
what are the what is a failure mode
that currently exists that you think there's
a lot of people working on it and
will likely be resolved soon
And then on the flip side, what is
a failure mode that you wish more people
were working on?
And whoever wants to answer, go for it. You can
all answer if you're excited, but if only a few of
you, go for it.
Maybe we can start, I'm still
kind of talking about fluctuation, but maybe
one thing that stresses me.
Is not okay,
understand the molecule hallucinate. Okay? Okay.
It's also kind of the wrong term. Let's
kind of put that aside. It can produce non factual
The problem is that it
it cannot indicate to us
where it's not certain. I mean, what would you
think You probably kind of
probably kind of have been meeting people
You probably have have have come across,
like, you've come sometimes across people at
always know everything. What would you think of
this person? Well, he cannot
possibly be a world expert in absolutely
everything. Okay? But
that's how LOMs behave. Okay?
So as a result, well, I mean, you
might be super expert, but you
are kind of less useful to me because I don't know
when I can trust him or I cannot. And
then you know, it is
to be it is
okay. There are two things here.
Number one is that the models
don't really indicate when they don't know.
They don't say I don't know that often.
Actually, this is changing. They are kind of now some models are
starting doing this kind of this is kind of now realized.
That's good. So kind of this is kind of one failure
mode. I wish kind of there was more research on
this. There are papers, some kind of, you know, like, spotlights
and so on in conference. I'm really happy that people are
looking into this, but it's not solved. Okay?
Ramon should tell you where he doesn't know.
Should be also kind of maybe kind of expressed confidence.
We can be developing some tools for that.
That's far from solved, number one. Number two,
is kind of even more disturbing
for me is
the confidence of the
model and it's a design thing
when the model is really kind of making
things up it doesn't
know it's really kind of producing some kind
of think is very, very convincing,
I think that's very dangerous. Should
be designing systems that
are making the model
really confident and really kind of, you know,
there should be a way when you speak
to a person. Right? I mean, this is how a recognized
a real expert. Is gonna tell
you sometimes I don't know. Number one. Number two
is going to say, well, I can
I'm not so sure here. Right? Want the models
to behave the same way. If we are
it. Yeah. That's great to hear. And
area where we're hoping more people focus on
that so we can keep moving forward.
I agree that calibration is very important
in in many, many respect, and it's not solved in
more people should work on that. I had another one.
Just to compliment. And it's about,
what happens when we know that
the effect was used
for training and
that fact is now false for Maybe it was false
from the beginning because was wrongly
in the training set. Or it just changed through time
and now it's false. So there are
many, many techniques that have
been proposed to to know,
work around that. But are far
from being good and in particular, they are not very good
at what I would call, the second
order fact. So suppose
you have a fact that says, and I'm
inventing now x equal three,
You see it's not very interesting,
but so that you get the point.
And if you find a technique
whether in context or
fine tuning or whatever to tell the model actually,
you know, x equal five.
It will remember that x
equal five, but it will not remember that
x square is now 25.
So the second order of fact, the the way
you use the fact has not been necessarily
modified. Actually, most of the time it's not. And
if you try to force it, it will actually
destroy way more information than you wanted.
So changing facts
in a model after it's been trained is actually a
still a hard task and it's a open
question to me.
Yeah. And pass it to Seyuan.
Yeah. My answer to this question is a little
bit of repetition what I always said, which is
I think tasks that are easily
verifiable and very well defined are
easy, and I think that will be solved very soon
even if if not perfectly right
now. But task that are
open ended, very hard to define, very hard to
verify, or those I think has long way to go.
Speaking of factuality, since we've been discussing
factuality, I think that uality is one
of them that feels very trivial to
verify, but it's actually open ended because
what is fact? I think this is like,
very difficult because there's no ground truth.
Fact. Fact consider it as fact
if there's a data that supports the statement,
But if more people's
data doesn't mean it's more true than the
other that was stated by less people,
that unclear, and
yeah. Like sometimes, I think with our menu statement
that I don't know if this factually true
or not, so I think this is, like,
one of areas where which is, like, very
more open ended than people think.
Perfect. Thank you all for sharing areas
that hopefully some of the people
in this room and others who are online
will put some effort into so we can
keep making progress in that space.
So another really popular topic,
today at this workshop and throughout the
conference, there are actually multiple sessions in the
conference about it, has been
evaluation and overfitting
benchmarks, has often been
a concern in the community, and this concern
continues to persist with large language
models. So I'm eager to have a
show of hands from all four of you.
So, you're gonna raise your hand yet
if you wanna say yes. So the question is,
yes or no, do you think we
are overfitting benchmarks as a community
for LLMs?
Okay. I
appreciate show of hands. So,
I guess the show of hands isn't as good of a filter as
I thought it might be, but I was gonna
say for all of you who said yes so
now, you can choose to answer
or not. If you think
we are overfitting, which you do,
our existing benchmarks still helping
us make progress despite the overfitting.
And then secondly, are there any solutions
or ideas we should keep
in mind to try to ensure that benchmarks
can help us make more
progress with or without overfitting.
Yeah. Yeah. I think the reason
we all agreed, I think, is that in machine
learning, whenever you put a metric or a benchmark,
people gonna go after it and then you're gonna
inevitably end up overfitting.
That's a bit unavoidable in in that sense.
In terms there was a
middle question. Basically,
like, are they helping us make progress? Yes.
And I think there is still something to be said because
with while it is important to have like one metric
that you say, like, let's go here, it's still
you can characterize the space of how you're doing. Right?
And I think that this is quite multidimensional.
A a a set of benchmarks
allows you to cover the space a bit more interestingly
than just having the one thing. So
often, unless they're completely saturated, it
is still useful to have to have
array of benchmarks as opposed to a single one.
And again, not an expert on this topic,
but I do know that at
least larger labs that make big models also
have their own internal benchmarks. Right? So
you can always overfit to the more academic
ones, but I do suspect that
bigger labs are running their own internal
benchmarks give them a bit more of
signal. Right? Not everyone can afford to have this, but
some of the bigger models I know do.
So Yeah. I think, benchmarks
are always going to be useful. But
we have to be careful about how we
use them. First, we should
we should generate more benchmark. There should be
like a potentially infinite amount of
benchmark. Way to do that is to try
to to
to parametrize them, to have
questions in this benchmark that have a hyperparameter
that can change So every time, you can
actually generate more
or different new questions
and answers. And so that becomes
a an environment parametric
benchmark. So you can have as
many as you want in in that setting, you
cannot really overfit particular question. You
can only overfit the distribution, which
is much more hard.
This is, of course, like, dreaming,
I think. But
the way to go around that is to
never stop creating new benchmarks.
A benchmark happens on a given day and for
a short amount of time, it's going to be
useful. And very quickly, it will not.
So there should be much more resources
devoted to have even more benchmark.
If it's not bad.
Can I just add a really quick layer of dreaming
on top of that? Mean, I'm sorry say the
words multi agent. And like, say you
could have some curricular like in a
dream, this adapting to the benchmarks
can be an objective of another agent itself.
And have something that coevolves. Right? And like this this
benchmark evolving in a dream land, you could
have it adapt it by something that is
whose objective it is to evaluate you.
Or some kind of, adversarial setting.
Yes. Yes. Absolutely.
Oh, yeah. So regarding the first question,
like, whether we are overfitting to benchmark, I
was actually only, like, half yes,
actually, because I think the answer is
true. But also, I think nowadays,
all of us kind of know that higher
benchmarks are not necessarily
doesn't necessarily mean they're better. I think
when new frontier models come in, we don't
really that model is better just because
it is has higher benchmark, but we probably
want a more like five eval,
like we try it out and see if it
feel it's better. So I think in some sense, I think they
are fine. Yeah. And
regarding the new question on whether benchmarks
are useful, I do think they're useful, and
I agree that we should never stop creating
new benchmarks. I almost think that
if we can make something as a benchmark, then
we almost like sold the task because once
we have a benchmark we can optimize for that,
I mean, there's a contamination issue and things
like that, but assuming we are not doing that, But there
are many problems where we just can't
don't know how to make a benchmark and
in that sense, I think making benchmark is very
important.
Well, maybe I can add a few comments.
Yes, we are
badly over fitting Well, one
promise that contamination, which was
kind of discussed even today,
it's a big, big problem, so we don't even know whether we
are doing proper measurement.
But another
danger is that
we benchmarks
okay. So you you need them because
you need to measure progress and what you can measure,
we can improve on. Right? The question is
kind of what you do with
those benchmarks. If you say, I want to be better at
math, agree. We just need more math
benchmarks, and you get a new new ones. You
need hidden ones. You need to even kind of to
hire companies to test you on things that you don't
know, even though, like, you know, to manual evaluation is
very, very important. It was
already mentioned. But
problem is that the reality is that right now,
the benchmark have become
part of the learning curriculum of the
model. So we are kind of just trying to get
there. And this is the recipe of training
my model. I want to kind of overfit on this benchmark
and also on the benchmark It
doesn't matter because it kind of matters. So the moment when you
start optimizing for some specific
benchmark is not a good benchmark anymore.
That's a problem. And,
so what is the way forward? One
way forward is to have more. Another way
forward is to have more
you know, human evolution kind of open
ended things. They came by Karina, they came others. I mean, they
have their own problems. But
another way is, like, to think
are we are those benchmarks
measuring the right thing? Okay?
And and the right thing can be
is an expert, you know, person is kind
of doing this in their job,
going to use this kind of system. Right?
And and and, know, not
really okay. What it kind of can solve this specific
problem.
How you do this kind of in the real world, that's
something that is not so easy kind of people
here, like, cooking into fresh questions. I mean,
thing is that many of the benchmarks
are measuring things
that just don't make sense.
I mean, for example, right,
you have things that are
up you're measuring
the capability of the language model
on multiple choice questions. You are
not even asking the model generate anything.
You are looking in the logs and internal
probabilities Okay. That's good. Tell you whether
the model knows the answer or not, but doesn't
tell you anything about the generating capabilities
and how the user is going to interact with
the model. That's kind of really
far away from the actual use case.
Yeah. Thank you all for sharing your
perspective on how benchmarks can be
useful despite the fact that they're we're
often overfitting to them. I think it's
really helpful to keep in mind that there can still
be signal despite overfitting.
And I really love, press love, what you were just talking
about of it's important to not just think
about overfitting, but also what are we measuring with those
benchmarks and what might be missing. So,
you are welcome to re answer this.
Or expand on it, but I'm curious to hear what the other three
panelists think about that in terms of
what are we currently missing
from benchmarks? Is there maybe something connected
to real world use usefulness that you wish
was incorporated in benchmarks that you're
not currently seeing today?
Yeah. I was saying, that ideally, we'd
like to replace Benchmark by what
I called environments.
And these environments are like, trying
to replace parts of the world that we want the model
to be good at. And if
we can have this, I think it's going to be more near
the kind of problems we actually want solve, and
it's going to be more generic.
So it evolved
in some cases, you can do that. I think
should always do that.
Can. I also like that idea of, right, if you're
doing it in an environment that ties back
a little bit to what you were saying before about having
benchmarks that can continue to evolve instead
of have such a short lifespan.
Yeah. Go for it, sweetie.
I wish there are more benchmarks
that can measure how well it
interact with humans, which is very difficult
to have in static bench especially
in academia. But things like, oh, can we
can the model ask the right clarification questions?
Can model
help human to solve the problem with rather
than solving the problem itself. And
so, yeah. Definitely
agree. Trying to
measure and somehow simulate that
user interaction component is an
extremely difficult and open challenge right now.
So I'm gonna say something a bit different. I think what's
on top of having more benchmarks, I think it's
also important to look at the quality because I've been
looking when actually, when you sit down
and look at some of the benchmarks
and the the quality of the answers, the
quality of what we're either training or even evaluating
even worse our models on, it's often not great.
And you don't really notice because we take benchmarks as
these god given things that we just need to
I think it's important to look at what we're doing
and potentially clean them up
which is a huge task. Right? But if we're gonna do more,
I'd also say we do better. I've
just added a a whole new dimension of of work
to this. Problem. Yeah.
Go for it, Prezilov. Yeah. Maybe kind of I cannot.
It's it's I mean,
you have been building several models. Right? And and
there's there's a conflict here
they want a better model, or
do you want a model that is better on the benchmarks?
And it's it's a decision
that people need to make I can tell you that
when we released the first version of Chase,
right, we had a model that
was, you know, the best one
in Arabic, and, in terms
of, let's say, performance on
English, it was maybe
about one point, you know, better than WAMA,
WAMA two at a time, Did
we release this model? We didn't.
We released another one that has was
22.5 points behind,
you know, smaller or so, one and a half
points behind Malama. Why?
Because the generations were visibly better
to us. As humans. We didn't care.
We are not in the business of claiming that we have something
that is better in English. We want a good
model for Arabic, and we wanted a good model
that actually people are going to use. I mean, if you look
at animals, we that, you know, kind of there are
publications, there are things. At the end of the day,
it's let's say, kind of j's. Right? It's by
far the most used one for Arabic. It's like 1,200,000
downloads on Hanging Face. Right? I mean, for
a specialized one for a language model. You know, the
competitors, like, I don't know, like, 10 times less or something.
So mean, that's
to me we need kind of to think how we measure success.
I mean, they they are they are also kind of, if you
go in faith, there
are certain models that
you go there. I mean okay. So if you
look again in the Arabic leaderboard,
if you look where JCS is not the first one.
It's probably now not I mean, like, each time there's a
new leaderboard, maybe it's kind of, you know,
at the top or near the top and then kind of quickly
kind of goes down maybe at position 10 or
20 or whatever it is. Or kind of if it's like,
you know, why? Because
there are people that in the business of going there and
overfitting. You know? Take, you know, some model and trying
to fine tune it. It's very, very easy to to game
just to kind of play this game. You
just say, okay. Here's the thing I sample from
a distribution. I do some reinforcement learning. I
do instruction tuning. Voila. Right? I'm
there. I mean, what the but think of it if nobody uses
this more. Right? And, actually, right, if the models
are even sometimes not available, And then
sometimes you see some kind of random username
that kind of dominates several leaderboards. I mean,
that's spam. Right? There's no signal
there. Right? Kind of you need to be
thinking what are we doing.
Right? And what is the thing that we want
to optimize? Do you want a good system?
Or do you want to be on the top of the leaderboard?
Yeah. Go for it, Sammy. I'm gonna make one comment
before more thing. Benchmarks
are useful, of course, to to have leaderboards
about, my model is better than yours.
I think they are also very important for science
to progress. Now, it's not about models,
it's that I have a new algorithm to make
this model better or this model better for
this task. And I need to convince a
reviewer too that it is actually better.
And, I I need ways and I think
benchmarks are what we've using
as a community And sure,
it's not perfect, but we need something like
that. Otherwise, we can't be in this room
together.
Maybe another one other thing to add is
that
it's it's a problem. The okay. The here's
the problem. Problem is that in the past,
we had a system to do one thing.
Okay? So that we had a model to do one thing.
Then we didn't discuss that much about
the problems with the benchmarks because
okay. Are evaluating models, not systems.
That's another problem. Now many
of the things mean,
in certain cases, somebody tells me, go ahead
and evaluate it online. Well, basically,
when I do things, I like
to put here the ones that are online
Here are the ones that actually I can download and I
can do it myself. Those that are online, I don't
even know. It's probably a system. It's probably not somebody.
I mean, I have no idea what the heck is this. You can say
it's 30,000,000,000, can be 300,000,000,000. I don't
know anything. Right? There can be a a
whole bunch of other things, agents and so on and
so forth. I don't know what is their prompt. So kind
of it's not it's not the
same thing. I cannot you cannot compare
against those. It can be also kind of can can't
give see this data and and and
and all possible things. Okay? If you want really
a plea a a kind of a clear ground
otherwise, you cannot evaluate things
properly. But in the past, we had
systems for one thing, Okay? And those
are models for one
thing. Let's say translation. Okay? If people are
not complaining that much about the evolution set,
but now we want
to have multiple things. First of all, it's very easy for me
to overfit. If I know what the
test sits is, I can generate synthetic data
that's somehow similar
like, and I can, like, push with reinforcement
learning the numbers as high as you want.
Okay? Now the problem is
the problem is that you end up is
very, very dangerous. It's less dangerous if you do
it with SFT. It much more dangerous if you
do it with reinforcement learning because you can
create very spiky distributions. We
can create systems that are extremely high on
these kind of tasks, and
kind of the quality the overall quality can
degrade much more. If you do use the SFT, the
overall degradation is kind of
less. And and
what I'm saying is it's irresponsible
to do this because you
end up with systems
that are clearly worse in many
other ways. So you are good on
the leaderboard, Right?
You kind of the better you get on the leaderboard, the worse
it actual performance of your system is.
Yeah. It's great to keep in mind that
benchmarks do give us signal, but if your
gents bench maxing for the point of bench
maxing without actually improving the
overall system, you're not
moving in a good direction. And it's why,
you know, having some more comprehensive
perhaps, benchmarks or benchmarks that can evolve over
time, as Sammy was mentioning, and making sure that
we're actually looking into what the benchmark
is and verifying, like,
like Mardo was mentioning and how Sue
Moon was mentioning of you know, just checking leaderboards
isn't sufficient. You also, you know, wanna
look at how it performs in practice for what you're
looking at and maybe do a little bit of vibe checking
as well. So it's really helpful to keep all of
these things in mind when we're
trying to look into benchmarks and thinking
about it. So another
thing, I know Arnold mentioned it at the very
beginning of or can't remember. Actually, it
was Arnold Rafan, so I apologize. One of you mentioned
it earlier on today. Something that we're
really excited about as part of the I can't believe
it's not better initiative is that
NERAPs actually, this year, now
has a negative results opt
for submissions in the main track, and this is
something we're really eager to have more
discussions about the process behind
science and where things are failing so we can have more
of that open discussion and, you know,
prevent replicated effort, so can all move
the field forward in a meaningful way.
And one thing that was noted,
in the call for papers is that
there is an extremely hard high
bar for these papers, and I think that's important. Right?
Because you wanna understand, like, why
is it a failure and what's going on.
But I think I'm curious hear from all of you
about is what would you wanna see in a great
negative result paper at NERIPS?
Maybe I can start by saying
the idea of having negative results in,
at neurons is not new.
Been tried many times, and it's failed
many times, unfortunately. But,
I think it's great that we try to make it
work. The the main reason why it
failed many times I mean, there are a couple,
but the first one is, when someone says
this doesn't work, there are so many
ways a thing cannot work. Most
of them are just because you didn't do it
well. And so,
so it's very easy to to
look bad, because you say
that this thing doesn't work. And
so you are not going to be very much encouraged
to actually tell us that this thing doesn't work
because you're you're like a you
look weak by telling us that actually
you might be be not thinking about
everything. So I think a good
paper that is a negative result is a paper that
cannot be attacked by any angle like
that. So it's going to be very
difficult but you have to actually find the reason
why it doesn't work. Which
also kind of means could make it work because
you could change this and then it worked. But
the negative result is still useful for
some reason. So, it is going to
be hard, but it's going to be very impactful.
If people are willing to play that much
harder game. So
maybe I I can add something. So
some colleagues actually in the
NLP community years ago
thought it's a very good idea to create a
journal of negative results.
Okay? Actually did And
in three years, the journal did not
receive a single submission. And
they shut it down. Okay? So
that's kind of the attitude of the community. Right?
And they thought it's very good, and that it has been
all kind of, you know, very good calls and, you know,
reasons and all that. I mean, the problem
is yeah. I mean, who wants
to say, well, I build systems
that don't work? Right? So so
mean, that being said,
there I mean, at the same time,
no matter what you work on, you probably
know after a while that certain things
don't work. And there are things that are kind of
common knowledge that those things don't work. Of
course, it would be interesting actually to say, no. No. No. I'm gonna
make it work. That's also very good research,
but, you know, you might it's
still good for a newcomer to to this
kind of topic to this area to
know those things have been tried. They don't work.
The problem is you don't know what was tried,
because the filter is that the ideas don't
work. It didn't get published. And it's
a problem. Now how can we what
we can do about it? One
thing that we can do is
to incorporate those things
into papers where we describe things that actually
work but to spend some time and to say,
we actually also tried this thing.
And it's not just us. It's kind of something that
many people have been trying. And it
doesn't work. But we need to specify. It doesn't
work in this specific condition because of
this and because of that. A real one, if you really want to
push it, I have seen some papers with negative results,
it's conferences. The it's not that they don't
exist, but they have to put extra
effort. There has to be analysis. They have to kind of
very clear documentation. Right?
It makes sense, what was done.
To me, it's easier actually to incorporate into
the systems, into the papers, what
things work say also a little bit about what
doesn't work. We can probably start there.
Yeah. Just big plus one to both of those. I I was
gonna say something similar to this. I think it is about
exploring the boundary of what works and doesn't and it's
often very brittle. So it is
much more convincing when you come with a paper saying, look,
I did make something work, so I know how to run
this code. But then showing these
are the boundaries that I've experienced. Right? And like this,
there should be more space in papers
to talk about that. And maybe it could be a a request. Right?
You have to have a section of what did you try and what
didn't work, or or tell us this. Right? You have to have a section of what did you try
and what didn't work, or or tell us tell us this. As well. But, yeah, plus one is basically
repeating what was said.
Yeah. Sorry. I don't have anything to add because I
actually have the exactly same question. I don't know what's
the right way to write negative result
paper because well, if you try to find negative
result, it's very easy. You just don't do
it well, and so I think what's
really important as a community is, like,
rather than, like, trying to find
negative result intentionally, I
I really like the proposal. Like, I think when we
try to make something work really, really hard,
we we try our best and
maybe it works in a certain scenario, but if we
can also implement the
practice of including when it doesn't
work, I think that would be much more convincing
and
I have a specific proposal that I just
thought about. Okay. Here's a proposal.
In some of our conferences, there
are sections where
we say, oh, maybe
ethical statement or or maybe
kind of reproducibility statement
or maybe, you know, kind of things like that,
or maybe limitation.
Right? If you think of the limitation,
there can be another section
that is out there which is
interesting negative results. So
So then get a when when this is a specific section,
this can encourage people actually to
fill report just so we have no limitations. We are kind of
seeing how our work
can be attacked by an LOM
automatically so that, you know, laser reviewers
give arguments to destroy us.
It reminds so I think one more thing
I wanted to say about negative results is that
if you want to convince someone that a negative
result is is, I mean,
are technique is wrong,
you need to be very strong about it. The best
is if you can show a proof
it is never going to work. It's not
that it doesn't work for this experiment,
it's never going to work in this case.
That's a very strong negative result.
And even that is hard to publish.
So even the strongest negative
result I remember
long time ago, my brother
had a negative result paper
showing that deep neural
network which were not called like that at the time maybe,
the the gradient would be would vanish
as you added more layers.
So it was the vanishing gradient problem.
And that paper was very strong
in in showing how it would vanish.
Nevertheless, it was very hard to publish and to convince
the you know, the the community at
the time. That, that
it was actually true. And actually, it
it led to ways to go around it
in particular the LSTM paper in a way,
was a way to go around the vanishing paper. So
a strong negative result can actually be
very good for the community. But it has to be
very principled.
And maybe but tangentially related
to this, I think we it's worth mentioning that I
think as a community, we're still quite lucky
in in this aspect for for for an experimental
science compared to others. We
do have relatively high reproducibility. If you look
at biochemistry or physicist or whatever, when
they do experiments, they struggle as a community
often is that you would want papers
replicating and seeing if this is true. Right?
With all the co sharing and and
in conferences or or open
source and so on, we're actually able
to often experiment with this ourselves. So,
but this is a big chunk of work
that we don't need to worry about at this
community, about is this even reproducible? So check.
That's already pretty good. And then the fact that we're already
thinking about negative results, I think shows that we're quite lucky
in that sense. So I think it's sometimes good to
give a nod to that as well.
So maybe maybe if I can add something,
to this remark about
the that it's very hard to
to to publish something that is true negative. I think
it's kind of part of a broader problem.
It's very hard to publish something
that is new.
And, you know, this is the thing that
this conference should be favoring.
But it's actually kind of hard with
the reviewers because
I mean, in certain cases,
I have some truly new work,
truly new problem, with truly new
kind of formulation, I prefer to
send it to some journal
kind of some of those, you know, attack or whatever.
Right? Because I know that the reviewers
are not going to be random. Are not going
to necessarily ask me okay. What
is the previous state of the art? We have
improvements? There's no previous state of the art. Right? Those
2% are very, very hard to publish.
And, so
we need to also rethink. Right?
And when you have negative results, it again
kind of goes against what
people have been assuming a paper should look like.
It's also kind of we have reviewers that are conditioned
in a certain way,
And, I mean, it's part of the growth of the
field. Have now trained a whole
generation of reviewers
that have seen reviews of
certain quality Right? And and,
so it probably is
most of them are kind of young. They don't have much experience.
Takes a little bit of experience to appreciate the depth
of certain ideas. So not
not sure how we can make sure that
truly good new ideas actually can emerge
past the filtering.
Yeah. I really appreciate, and I'm sure everybody
here does as well, all of the advice about
how to share negative results and all
of the hard work and steps that are required
to really confirm for yourself
it is a negative result before sharing it. And I really
love the idea of thinking about well,
maybe we should be trying to share
some pointers in our papers with positive
results about what didn't work. Because
I think, to Prezlev's point, that's of
the challenges. If you're newer in the field, you might not know
some of this tribal knowledge. Right, that, Marty, you
were mentioning that we accumulate over time.
And so it's it can be very
helpful to help kick things off. And I
know we're getting closer to the end of the
panel. So if someone
in the audience wants to ask the panel a
question, I'd encourage you to raise
your hand quickly
There we go.
I can also give you mine.
That's fine. You can borrow from me. Yeah.
Okay. This one works. Think you were
first. No?
I kinda have a two part question on benchmarking.
I'm gonna limit it to whatever your favorite part
is because we've got a couple minutes. Okay.
I'll be quick. So does there
come a point at which
having enough benchmarks
makes it so that benchmarks
actually gives you like a better overall model.
And, I also would like to ask
the panelist what's what their opinion is on,
human preference benchmarks. Like,
Adam Marina. I think that is something
that, for example, I use when
I like,
Yeah. Go for it, Suwan.
Yeah. Sorry. Pass the mic.
Yeah. So the question is about, like,
what we think about the
benchmark based on human preference, like Elena Reyna.
Think when it came out, there was a time
when we were relying on static benchmarks
without like, human actually look
at the answers. And in that sense, I think it
was a great progress because I
remember correctly, there was one of the earlier
efforts that like, tried
to do that for the first time. Like, human actually,
like, look into that, don't just
trust the benchmark numbers and so on. So I think
that was a very meaningful progress.
Nowadays, I think we do that, and then
but then just to trust this,
like, human preference, I think the
problem is
the notion of preference is very ill defined.
It can be
heavily rely on what population
is labeling human preference,
and I also don't think human
preference necessarily mean
better Chris or better model.
There are many tasks where
there are certain aspect that human preference can
measure well, like stylistic component but
if it about, like, how accurate
it is, I think human preference is not the right
metric. And we actually also have
a paper in this
in this iCLEAR that shows that,
like, depending on the population, the optimum
preference can be very different,
and sometimes human preference might be
toward how funny the response is, and that can
lead to little, like, biased
model to be preferred. So, yeah. I think it
is very nuanced.
Thanks. That was a great You were a great
second answer. And, yep, I was gonna say, let's go for
the next question. Yeah. Thank you very much.
I want to get back to the first question of this
panel. Actually, what surprises,
me personally why,
thing that should be already solved, but
it hasn't been solved. So, my
personal thing I many things were were were
named and were really great.
Or really interesting and very important problems,
but my personal thing is memory.
What I mean is that,
you know, what how people are are
are being learned, how being taught they do some
work and they naturally learn to become they
naturally become better. We don't do this
credit update during the, you
know, doing stuff. Right? And language
models cannot do this. We We
have gradient updates, and we
have also something like in context learning.
But as soon as you just run out of the context,
you're you're done. You have to start from
the zero point. So people had tried
to do this On the one part, they're
trying to create some databases such as, like,
memory m d file. Right?
And write, something inside
this file and drive from this file. On the
the other part, people try just try to make,
to feed more context in in interest
optimization techniques
like slamming window attention, some,
group query attention, whatever.
But there's probably like, middle
ground that makes this
recurrent memory it's still
not I mean, it's still very, very hard. I
mean, we're trying to do this, and I think it's pretty, very
hard to make it actually natural
neural memory. So, my question
is like, do you do you agree that maybe we
should like resolve this
bottleneck What's your opinion? Maybe there are some
works that are already, you know, doing this.
I don't know. Thank
you.
I I think that
you know, okay, obviously, there's this work already
going there. I
think that maybe part of the reason is not resolved.
Is that there are so many
other problems that are perceived as more important.
Right? Initially, categorizations are so huge
that, you know, you have to do something
about them or, you know, other things. Right?
Or maybe kind of safety, kind of not other
things that are kind of in more immediate
you know, the things that people told they should be working
on. Some kind of there was more advancements on
some kind that has been less. I think
that memories part
of a bigger problem bigger problem
is personalization. We have I
think that that's a big big thing.
Right? That that, I mean,
you have Chargebeeq can kind of remember
things about you, start modeling you, and all
that, something that search engines have been doing for years.
Right? So that's a direction that is
going to happen. It's obviously
related to memory. So there's going to be more
and more research in that direction.
By the need for personalization.
Yeah. I think that makes a lot of sense and helps
highlight one of the key things in the
field right now is that there's a lot of
open questions and a lot of really exciting
work to do despite all of the progress that
has been made. And so memory is one of
those areas, and there's lots
of other areas. And so really excited to
see how the field keeps moving forward.
And we're gonna use that as
a nice way to wrap up the panel. So let's give
our panel all a round of applause.
Thank you all so much. We really, really appreciate
you taking time out of your busy schedules to
share some of your insights with us.
Pleasure. You so much. Yeah. Thank
you. You're welcome. Very nice for coronary
Okay. And
stay tuned because there will be
the award So me just one second.
I'm setting it up. Exactly.
Gonna hand it off to Arnaud, do some
closing notes. We will have
about five more minutes of content
So feel free to stick around, hear
who wins the awards, and
all of the exciting things that are gonna be wrapping
up just about right now.
Sorry? No. I think I can do it like this.
I just need to taste
the winner of the poster award onto
the slide. I'm not sharing.
Right? Okay. Good.
And then we can get to it.
Alright. So let me reconnect
here.
Okay.
So we're getting to the last
part of this workshop. Thank you all for
coming here today.
Especially also this late last
minutes. Please don't forget
to take down your posters. Okay?
Like take them after
I finish talking, but do take them.
And The biggest thing I want to say at this
point is a thank you
to all of you here in the room of course as I just
said as the attendees. And also
partially authors. But yeah, also to the authors
who couldn't be here today, who or already
left. Thank you so much for all your submissions
and the great work. Almost
more important to reviewers, we had
81 reviewers that Fan showed earlier in
the day. You so much. Without all
your help, we couldn't actually run this workshop.
The same of course goes for the speakers and
panelists. Great job of those
today. I see one or two still here. So thank you
so much for participating.
The other organizers that aren't here today
Fan was showing them earlier
They helped a lot in the background
over the last months. It's
just that due to visa or other,
arrangements they couldn't really make it
in person. But big thank you to
them and advisers. And lastly,
of course, the conference and especially
also workshop chairs of this
IKEA conference. As well as our friends
at Slides Live. So thanks for the great job today.
Thank you. And then
stay in touch. Is the link and the
QR code to our website. We always look for new
volunteers to help run future editions of this workshop
in you find our mission, our ideas
interesting, you like to promote
also negative results that have been rigorously,
researched please get in touch.
And that brings me to the last item,
the awards that I know you're all here for not for
the thank you. So, we will have
three awards. The first one is the end tropic
paper award which comes with a really
big surprise. So the one where we said, wow,
really can't believe that. There's
also the didactic paperwork just a
paper that just a great job at, yeah,
deductively explaining and narrowing
down the issue. And lastly,
thing that we decided today here on the spot,
the best poster award. Looking at
the posters. What poster was actually
really well designed and
showed great research quality. So without
further ado, we don't have any print outs,
just stay at your seats, but let's hear
an applause for the winners. And Tropic paper
awards goes to
curing time producers, upsell position devices,
between LLM and humans. Great
job and thanks for contributing.
The didactic paper award is for
selected safety trip safety trap. How
LMS and scaling and alignment fail to generalize
across minority demographic?
And lastly, the poster one
that I just inserted, that's why there was the one
minute delay, is for our
senior who had done retrieve generate prompting
LLMs for synthetic data and dense retrieval I
think it's over there in case you wanna have a
look. Yeah. That's
it. Thank you and, yeah.
Have a safe trip home.
See you next year.